<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of faith, and of some principal fruits thereof Deliuered in two sermons, vpon the third chapter of the epistle of Paul to the Ephesians, verse the 12. With some additions and enlargements, tending to the satistaction of such as are in doubt, whether they haue faith or no, and to the comforting of such as are troubled about the weakenesse of their faith. By G. Throgmorton, minister of the word of God.</title>
            <author>Throgmorton, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13755</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1403</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13755)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1403)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 978:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of faith, and of some principal fruits thereof Deliuered in two sermons, vpon the third chapter of the epistle of Paul to the Ephesians, verse the 12. With some additions and enlargements, tending to the satistaction of such as are in doubt, whether they haue faith or no, and to the comforting of such as are troubled about the weakenesse of their faith. By G. Throgmorton, minister of the word of God.</title>
                  <author>Throgmorton, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 223, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. L[egat] for William Sheffard, and are to be sold at his shop, at the entring in of Popes-head Alley, out of Lumbarde street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; pages marked, torn and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1403:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1403:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF FAITH, AND OF SOME PRINCIPAL FRVITS THEREOF.</p>
            <p>Deliuered in two Sermons, vpon the third Chapter of the Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Verſe the 12.</p>
            <p>With ſome additions and Enlargements, tending to the ſatisfaction of ſuch as are in doubt, whether they haue Faith or no, and to the comforting of ſuch as are troubled about the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their Faith.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. Throgmorton,</hi> Miniſter of the Word of God.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 3.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In whom we haue boldneſſe and acceſſe, with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence by the faith of him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> for <hi>William Sheffard,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the entring in of Popes-head Alley, out of Lumbard-ſtreet. 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:1403:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1403:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> TREATISE OF FAITH, <hi>AND</hi> SOME FRVITS THEREOF.</head>
            <div type="sermon">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>EPHES. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>In whom wee haue boldneſſe and acceſſe, with confidence by the faith of him.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle in the former ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, had by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles ſet foorth the glory of the Goſpel, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1403:3"/> his Office, and Miniſterie in preaching of it, aduancing it farre aboue the Law, and the Miniſterie of the Church in former ages. The Goſpel he commends, and ſets forth eſpecially by the ſubiect mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereof, which is Ieſus Chriſt. In this verſe, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth his praiſe of the Goſpel, from the ſauing fruits and effects, as its recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by faith, and Chriſt the ſubiect matter thereof right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehended.</p>
               <p>The principall ſcope of the Apoſtle in this verſe, after his commendations of the Goſpel, is, to ſhew the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of faith in the goſpel apprehending Chriſt, aboue all naturall faith, and confidence in any creature, and aboue all faiths, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions in the world, as the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1403:3"/> onely ſure and infallible meanes of ſaluation. This excellencie of true ſauing faith in Chriſt, is ſet foorth from the vertues, or fruites it brings foorth in the heart, and ſoule, or inner man of him that hath it, ſuch as no other faith, or any other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that leads vs to any other creature, or meanes, or name vnder heauen, or in any other Goſpel or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine can breed, that is, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that acceſſe to God by Manuduction, with that confidence, and freedome of ſpeach; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee inferres by way of exhortation in verſe 13. that they ſhould ſhew forth theſe vertues of their faith in all afflictions, and not faint.</p>
               <p>The Expoſition of the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuduction,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1403:4"/> or leading by the hand to God, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. Which being performed by Chriſt our Mediatour the Sonne of God, taking vs by the hand, we goe with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; confidence to God This wee haue in, and by Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> The neceſsitie whereof, is raiſed from this ground ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally; That whereas the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and his poſteritie were caſt out of Paradice from all fellowſhip with God, and from the tree of Life, the way ſhut vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.24.</note> 
                  <hi>and kept with a Sword drawne, full of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and Horrour;</hi> Chriſt Ieſus the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> not onely opens the way againe by <hi>his blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>and makes a new liuing way,</hi> but takes vs by the hand to lead vs to God,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1403:4"/> with boldneſſe and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, remoouing all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of feare, and the ſword ſhaken. This is alſo oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to that going to God by the old Church vnder the Law, at mount Sinay, in the giuing of the Law, and firſt Couenant of workes, by the Manuduction of <hi>Moſes</hi> their Mediatour, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19. They had not this Manuduction with this confidence: they ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farre off trembling, and might not goe vp into the mount to God: <hi>Yea ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible was the ſight, that</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>himſelfe</hi> their Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour <hi>ſaid, I feare and quake.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.21. And whereas all this came originally by receiuing, and admitting the deuill and his counſell, &amp; beleeuing his falſe goſpel
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1403:5"/> and promiſes: So contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all this good comes to vs, by beleeuing Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Son of God, whom God hath ſent from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vs, to redeeme and ſaue vs,<note place="margin">Acts 7.37.</note> 
                  <hi>that great Prophet whom God hath raiſed vp to vs, of our brethren like to vs,</hi> and by receiuing him for our King, Prieſt, and Prophet by faith, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,) ſuch a one as God hath ſent, and giuen him to vs. Alſo by faith in <hi>Moſes</hi> the people had acceſſe to God, and by taking, and following him their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, they came neerer to God, and God to them, then any other Nation and people, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.7. <hi>What Nation is there to whom the gods come ſo neere to them, as our God is neere to vs in all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1403:5"/> that wee call to him for,</hi> yet had not they by <hi>Moſes</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo neere to God, nor with that confidence, as now all Nations haue by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth open manifeſtation and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,<note place="margin">Such as were of for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and free ſpiri s to expreſſe themſelues boldly without ſeare of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, were called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſt Rhet. lib. 2.</note> with glorious liberty which ſtands in lifting vp of the face &amp; countenance, and in freedome of ſpeech: its oppoſed to the effects of the ſentence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Law, when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactours and guiltie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, arraigned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced by euidence of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditements, that they can ſay nothing for themſelues, beeing abaſhed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, haue both their mouthes ſtopped, and their faces couered, and ſo carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away to execution. This
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1403:6"/> appeares in the arraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſentence paſſed vpon <hi>Caine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene 4.13, 14.</note> which made him crie out, that <hi>his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was greater then hee could beare, becauſe hee was cast out from the earth, and from Gods face hee ſhould bee hidden hauing</hi> his owne face, as couered with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſhame, neuer to come to appeare before God, to ſacrifice or pray to him. <hi>But hee that beleeueth in Chriſt ſhall not be aſhamed.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.11. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man</hi> after the ſentence of death was paſſed on him, his face was couered, and hee had out of the Kings preſence, neuer to appeare more before him. And this is the ſtate of all the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, vpon the laſt ſentence of condemnation paſſed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1403:6"/> them, that <hi>they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhed with euerlaſting perdition</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>from the face and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9 neuer to come and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him, nor to ſpeake, or to pray to him, or to praiſe him, and for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of face and ſhame, wiſh the mountaines to fall on them, and the rockes to couer them. Contrarie to this woefall eſtate of the damned, is this bleſſed and glorious <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Saints by the ſentence of the iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of life in Chriſt that without ſhame or fear, they may come befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God <hi>with open face,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. (<hi>and not as</hi> Moſes <hi>with his face couered)<note place="margin">verſe 13.</note> may behold the glory of the Lord with open face, and bee changed into it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 18.</note>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:1403:7"/> For hauing our ſinnes par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and our perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into fauour with God, wee may behold his face and glory, as reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in iuſtification, and ſo are changed into it more and more, in ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from glory to glory. Whatſoeuer boldneſſe of face, and glory of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or libertie of ſpeach, wee may haue towardes men, in and by our ſelues, and our workes; wee haue none towards God but by Faith in Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.1. Firſt the Law <hi>indites, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, and ſtops our mouth,</hi> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. ſhame and confuſion couers our faces, and then <hi>Chriſt lifts vp our head,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Thou art my glory, and the lifter vp of my head:</hi> Yea, hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noints
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1403:7"/> our head with oyle, &amp; giues vs the oyle of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for the ſpirit of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.20, 27. as God hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted oyle to make the face to ſhine gloriouſly. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore contrarily, by the law in humiliation, they caſt durt on their heads, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered their faces in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their guiltineſſe, and in dayes of faſting the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.16.</note> Now Chriſt our high Prieſt was annointed with this oyle of gladneſſe aboue his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that it might lift vp his face for vs, in the ſight and preſence of God to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him, and wee receiue an anointing from this holy One, and hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noints our faces with oyle of ioy, for this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1403:8"/> word ſignifies ſpecially freedome, and glory of ſpeech in prayer, or praiſes of God, and thankeſgiuings, for in Chriſt wee haue a new mouth, a new ſpeach, tongue, and language of Canaan. The end of mans creation being chiefely to glorifie God; <hi>Adam</hi> was created with an excellent mouth and tongue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to glorifie him, which was his greateſt glory, life, &amp; happines: but by heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Sathans blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous mouth, and tongue, belying and diſhonouring God, and beleeuing it, he and all his poſteritie, haue loſt their naturall mouth, tongue, and language, and haue the mouth and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Satan, readier to blaſpheme and curſe God,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1403:8"/> then to pray to him, or to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe him; and being man become earth, and lacking the Image and Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie of God, and <hi>borne of the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſpeakes of the earth,</hi> as an earth-worme, with an earthly mouth riſing out of the duſt: As Satan is a lyer, ſo is euery man from the wombe, going aſtray, and ſpeaking lies. Therefore Chriſt giues a new mouth, tongue and language, if we hearken to him as our only Prophet and <hi>Rabbi,</hi> and a new <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by his ſpirit of Glory in vs, according to his gracious couenant in Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. And <hi>I will make this my couenant with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaith the Lord: My ſpirit that is vpon thee, and my words which I haue put in thy mouth, ſhall not depart
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1403:9"/> out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeede, nor out of the mouth of the ſeede of thy ſeede from henceforth and for euer.</hi> Therefore Chriſt is called the Truth. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6. But firſt he is the Way, then the Truth; our Way to God, and our <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as Prieſt, and then is he the Truth, and giues vs a new mouth.</p>
               <p>But theſe particulars ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare more fully in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations: only thus much for vnfolding the text, and the ſenſe of the words.</p>
               <p>Wherein wee conſider two parts. 1. The Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of Faith in Chriſt ſet forth by two vertues or workes in the heart and inner man.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Acceſſe to God, or Manuduction with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1403:9"/> or confidence, or a confident acceſſe to God by Manuduction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Glory of face with liberty of ſpeech.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The limitation of this excellencie and of theſe vertues; They are not in the whole man and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is ſo farre, as he is in Chriſt, not as he is or euer was in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> or as he is in nature, in the fleſh, and world, or as he is in any other eſtate and condition in this life, or that any man can haue in any other Religion then by Faith in Chriſt. And whereas the childe of God may complaine that hee finds and feeles contrary to all this, feare, trembling, flying from God, ſhame of face for his ſinnes, and his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1403:10"/> mouth often ſtopped, and not able to pray or praiſe God:</p>
               <p>Anſwer is here made; It is true, ſo farre as we are not in Chriſt, and haue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and fleſh in vs; but as we are in Chriſt, we haue all this contrary good. 1. <hi>De Iure,</hi> though not <hi>de facto,</hi> by right, though not by full poſſeſſion. 2. Wee haue theſe in ſome meaſure, though mixt with contrary corruptions. 3. We may haue more, if the fault be not in our ſelues. 4. We ſhall haue all theſe in full meaſure. 5. Theſe are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs in Chriſt, and our Faith in Chriſt will grow vp to theſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe with the increaſings of God and of Chriſt, if we pray, as <hi>Paul</hi> here doth for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1403:10"/> theſe <hi>Epheſians,</hi> ſo they may haue all this in Chriſt and that their Faith may grow and haue theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues working in them, as in the verſes following, <hi>verſe</hi> 16, 17, 18. which imply, that they had them not as yet from Chriſt, as they ſhould haue hereafter, but were only laid vp and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The ſumme then is, that no Faith, nor Religion giues that acceſſe to God, with that boldneſſe, ſo cheerefull and glorious a countenance, ſuch a mouth to praiſe God, to pray, and ſpeake freely to God, to powre out our hearts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, that giues ſuch a Spirit of prayer, and of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption to cry <hi>Abba</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to make a man bold
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1403:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:1403:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1403:12"/> to plead with God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſtand vpon interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with God, and to parle with him, eſpecially when Satan, ſinne, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence accuſe.</p>
               <p>Now theſe vertues are not ſanctifying graces in vs in their full perfection, but they are ſuch bleſſings and benefits in Chriſt, as Faith drawes from Chriſt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in which Chriſt they are, as in the propper naturall ſubiect, roote, and fountaine and Head, and which Faith drawes and receiues from Chriſt or poſſeſſeth in him, and therefore he ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. and ſo I come to the obſeruations. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in whom, that is in Chriſt. By Chriſt dwelling in vs, we haue and exerciſe theſe vertues of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1403:12"/> Chriſt; or Chriſt ſhewes himſelfe to be in vs, and we to be in him by theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. All ſauing good things in vs, are ſauing vertues, in and from Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>To ſhew forth the vertues of him that hath called you out of darkeneſſe.</hi> As the ſoule ſhewes it ſelfe to be in the body by the life and vertues it exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in the body, ſuch as the body it ſelfe hath not by its naturall humors: So Chriſt exerciſeth ſuch ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in the heart and ſoule of a Chriſtian, as the heart and reaſonable ſoule haue not naturally.</p>
               <p>As a man ſhewes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to dwell in a houſe, by the wiſedome, authoritie, power he exerciſeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: So Chriſt to dwell in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1403:13"/> vs by faith as in his houſe, when he exerciſeth his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in vs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Whoſe houſe ye are if ye hold faſt your confidence and hope of your reioycing, &amp;c.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30, 31. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. <hi>As ye haue receiued Chriſt Ieſus the Lord, ſo walke in him:</hi> And by his life, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and ſtrength to doe all things, and not by the ſtrength of nature, and of your naturall ſpirit, as <hi>Paul, Philip.</hi> 4.13. <hi>I can doe all things by the helpe of Chriſt ſtrengthning me.</hi> Rom. 8.10. <hi>If Chriſt be in you, the bodie is dead in regard of ſinne, but the Spirit is life in regard of righteouſneſſe,</hi> that is, the bodie lies dead from ſinfull actions and motions, from which a mans naturall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, wit, and pollicy can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1403:13"/> reſtraine him, and his bodily members to make them lye dead, but rather quicken and powerfully ſway them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.15. and 7.5. <hi>The paſſions of ſinnes which are by the Law, haue force &amp; vigour in our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to bring forth fruit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death,</hi> and <hi>Romanes</hi> 6.12. but if Chriſt be in vs, he deads theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the paſſions of ſinnes or ſinfull paſſions, that they cannot worke in our bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and earthly members; <hi>For they that are Christs haue crucified the fleſh with the affections and the lusts,</hi> Gal. 5.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> As Satan ſhewes his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation in man as his houſe poſſeſſing as a ſtrong man the pallace of the minde,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.21</note> and heart in peace, by the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1403:14"/> vigour hee exerciſeth in ſwaying their minds, wils, and luſts, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44. 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 4.4. So Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                  </note>We are the children of the firſt Reſurrection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of Chriſt, riſen from the dead, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. by the greateſt vertue and power of Chriſt quickning the dead, 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 3.21. Wee are not only begotten of Chriſt, by vertue of his Propheticall office, as he is light, as Hypocrites only inlightned are: but we are begotten of Chriſt by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Prieſtly office as crucified for vs, vnto A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption and Iuſtification of life, and by vertue of his Kingly office, as riſen from the dead to Sanctification, and participation of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1403:14"/> nature, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. As Chriſt was diſcerned and differenced from all the ſons of men, to be knowne to be the Sonne of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. by his reſurrection from the dead; as the firſt begotten from the dead, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18. So are all we his yonger brethren, by the ſame Spirit of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er raiſing vs to a new nature and life with him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4, 5. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1. and 2.12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.6. we are diſcerned and differenced from all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſonnes of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> That we may know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we haue Chriſt in vs or no, we muſt examine, tempt, and trie our minds, hearts, wils, affections, what vertues of Chriſt worke in them and ſway them; ſuch as are propper to Chriſt,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1403:15"/> and which no creature elſe can exerciſe in vs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10. <hi>As we beare in our bodies the dying of the Lord Ieſus,</hi> that is, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt miſeries and afflictions, <hi>So the life of Ieſus is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested in our mortall fleſh,</hi> that is, his greateſt quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, comforting vertue, when no creature can doe our mortall bodies any good, in ſickneſſe or in death, or other infirmities. Chriſt is not only our light, but our light of life; that is, in whom we haue not only light of knowledge, but the ſame a quickning knowledge, putting life in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our wils, and affections, &amp; bodily members to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe what we know. The Hypocrites light of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is like the candle
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1403:15"/> light, which quickens no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: the Saints light of ſauing Knowledge, is like the Sun-light, which quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens hearbs, trees, plants: our light of naturall reaſon, Philoſophy, Pollicy, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo quicken vs, and make vs ſo liuely and vigorous to good duties, as this light of the ſauing Knowledge of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.20, 21, 22. Let vs ſhew forth the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of Chriſt our light in vs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. A man may haue a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull light of Knowledge in the lanthorne of his braine, and yet his heart, will, and affections lye as dead as ſtones from deſire or endeauour to embrace or practiſe the good hee knowes, and haue no ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from Chriſt, to liue,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1403:16"/> walke and fructifie.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> This is for comfort to ſuch, as though they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not feele Chriſt in them, nor faith poſſeſſing Chriſt; as long as Chriſt ſhewes himſelfe to be within by ſuch vertues exerciſed in them, they may know themſelues to bee in the faith, and that Chriſt by faith is in them, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. For as many haue Satan in them, that doe not know or feele, or beleeue Satan to be in them: So many haue Chriſt, &amp;c. and as many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine Satan in them, by receiuing his lying Goſpel, and promiſes of wealth, peace, comfort by ſinning, and his temptations and perſwaſions to ſinne: So we receiue Chriſt when we beleeue and receiue his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1403:16"/> perſwaſions, and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to good duties, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the words of exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and beleeue his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and gladly embrace his word. Therefore ſuch as ſo did, were baptized into Chriſt for ſeale and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that Chriſt was in them, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. 2. <hi>Iohn verſe</hi> 9. See <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.23. <hi>If any man loue mee, hee will keepe my words, and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will loue him, and we will come vnto him, and make our abode with him. Adam,</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> receiued Satan into them, when they receiued his counſels and temptations, and ſuffered themſelues to bee ſwayed thereby; So co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarily we receiue Chriſt. If <hi>when wee giue place to wrath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4.26 27.</note> 
                  <hi>we giue place to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1403:17"/> Diuell,</hi> counſelling and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing vs thereto; then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily wee giue place to Chriſt and receiue him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts, when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his Goſpel of peace, counſelling, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs peace, and loue, by reaſons from the Goſpel, that is, from his loue and peace towards vs. Euery one that harbours willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his heart any knowne ſinne, and ſinfull ſuggeſtion of Satan, he intertaines Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; the malicious man hath a furious Diuell, the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton a voluptuous Diuell. So he that regards no ſinne in his heart, but caſts it out, Chriſt perſwading him thereto by his Goſpel, and not the Law alone infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him by terrors; He that turnes from ſinne vpon
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1403:17"/> ſuch ſuggeſtions, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, perſwaſions, as Chriſt makes to him, he receiues Chriſt by faith firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> And Faith beleeuing and receiuing Chriſt for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and only <hi>Rabbi,</hi> to be his Diſciple, and as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Way and Truth, it goeth before Repentance, which is nothing elſe but a wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in Chriſt, as we firſt receiued him by faith; ſhewing forth the vertues of Chriſt, and the life of Chriſt to walke as he hath walked. For Repentance is the life and vertue of Chriſt receiued as our way, Truth, and Life, and made all our Wiſedome, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Sanctification, and Redemption, and our light of life. What is Repentance but liuing and walking in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1403:18"/> Chriſt? For out of Chriſt euery motion is to death, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd hell; and can a man walke in Chriſt, before hee haue Chriſt by faith in his heart, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.6. <hi>As yee haue receiued Chriſt Ieſus the Lord, ſo walke in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee that all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing good things, are ſauing vertues in and from Chriſt. Now how, and by what meanes, do we receiue and draw theſe vertues from Chriſt, or inioy them in him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is only by faith of him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, by Faith receiuing or going to Chriſts perſon, pitching on him alone as reuealed and offered in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">By Faith of him.</note>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> Faith in Chriſts perſon, Name, is the only meanes of receiuing all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1403:18"/> vertues from Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.16. When we beleeue the Goſpel and glad tidings offering vs Chriſts perſon with all his benefits and vertues, and behold him to be ſuch a one towards vs, as the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel reueales and offers him to vs, that is, as 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. our Wiſedome, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Sanctification, and Redemption, our King, Prieſt, and Prophet; then is he indeede become ſuch a one towards vs, and we are made ſuch in him, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Beholding as in a loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king glaſſe,</hi> viz. the Goſpel, the glory of the Lord, with open face, we are changed from glory to glory; For in the Goſpel, God ſets forth Chriſt before our eyes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:1403:19"/> as the Mercy-ſeate was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted and lifted vp before the eyes of the people, that all may looke vp to him as <hi>the only Propitiation through faith in his blood,</hi> and ſo finde mercy and peace with God. Faith lookes vp to this Propitiation or Mercy ſeate, and to this brazen Serpent thus lifted vp in the preaching of the Goſpel, and ſo finds healing vertue. It directs our thoughts and deſires to Chriſt in the ſenſe of all ſinne and miſery, as offered in the Goſpel for cure, and ſo receiues reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. <hi>Iſay</hi> 45.22. Looke vnto mee and yee ſhall be ſaued, all the ends of the earth, &amp;c. Looke not vnto lying vanities.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note>O fooliſh <hi>Galathians,</hi> who hath bewitched your
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1403:19"/> eyes, that is, corrupted your minds and iudgements, and drawn away your thoughts and deſires from Chriſt, that ye ſhould not looke vp to him, who by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is ſo cleerely manifeſted and deſcribed before your eyes: that yee ſhould not obey the Truth, beleeuing Chriſt to be ſuch a one to you, as the Goſpel offers him to you; but looke a ſquint to circumciſion and workes, and other meanes of ſaluation. Beleeuing the Word of the Goſpel, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs Chriſt, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the ſame gladly, we receiue Chriſts Perſon and all that is his, and inioy them by this only meanes as fully as any creature can inioy any naturall good, by any naturall meanes, as trees
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1403:20"/> inioy the earth and ſap of it by their roots, ſo by faith in the Goſpel wee inioy Chriſts perſon, and all the ſappe of the Spirit of Life in him, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.6, 7. As the members inioy the Life and Spirits of the Head, by the bond and vnion of the nerues and arteries: So we the members of Chriſt by this Faith, receiue the ſpirit of life from Chriſt our Head, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. with <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2, 5, 14. As meate is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and inioyed by eating, light by looking on it; So is Chriſt by Faith. By Faith in the Goſpel, and promiſes we know Chriſt, we taſte him, and feede on him. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. Wee are rooted in him, built on him, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. vnited to him. By it we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his Perſon, and are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1403:20"/> begotten by him into his Nature and life, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.12, 13. By Faith we goe to his Perſon and receiue life, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.40. <hi>Ye will not come vnto me, that ye might haue life;</hi> and wee <hi>are made liuing ſtones by comming to him this liuing Stone,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. By this Faith we are built on him as on a Rocke, <hi>and the gates of Hell cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt vs,</hi> Math. 16. By Faith we walke in him, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. We eate his body, and drinke his blood, that is, we inioy all the Diuine vertues of his Godhead, and the merits of his Perſon in all his ſufferings, and that fulneſſe of the Godhead as dwelling in him bodily, that hee is Emanuel God with vs, and we are filled with all fulnes of God, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1403:21"/> all this only by beleeuing the Goſpel, that there is no facultie or vertue of ſoule or body, of man or any creature that can inioy any naturall good belonging to it, more fully and ſurely, then we may inioy Chriſt, and his Perſon, life, merits, vertues by Faith in the Goſpel only and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. Hereby we know him, we taſte him, we are rooted in him, built on him, vnited to him, married to him. Such is the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie and vertue of Faith in the Goſpel, that by it, the Sonne is ours, we haue and poſſeſſe him for our owne, euen his Perſon as our Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and his vnſearchable riches. See 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.9, 10, 11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Would we then inioy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1403:21"/> Chriſt, and his benefits? there is no meanes but his Word, and Goſpel im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by Faith; and this meanes is infallible, and all-ſufficient by Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Therefore care to get nothing, but Faith in the Goſpel, that the word of Chriſt may dwell plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly in vs, and then Chriſt himſelfe, with all his riches, and ſauing benefits are in vs, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.16. Wee neede not take thought, who ſhall aſcend vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, or who ſhall deſcend into the deepe: if the word be neere vs in our mouth, and in our Heart, then Chriſt deſcending, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending, both abaſed, and exalted, crucified, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and all-ſufficient to Saluation is ours, and in vs,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1403:22"/> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4, 6, 7, 10. Say not, what may I doe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine eternall life, and as <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.29. to worke the workes of God, to ſerue him, that wee may earne the bread of life; This is all the worke that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, and meanes of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining all ſauing good, to beleeue in him, whom hee hath ſent, firſt from Heauen to Earth by incarnation, &amp; now to all of vs, by the preaching of the Goſpel, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.17. &amp; <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.6. receiuing the promiſe of Chriſt by the Goſpel, wee are made one body with him, and the whole Church, and inheritors of all the ſame ſauing good: Chriſt hath ordained, and Sanctified this meanes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and infallibly to conuey
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1403:22"/> himſelfe into vs, his ſpirit, life, righteouſneſſe, merits, and not the Lawe, or any workes, or merits of man, or any creature, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4. Obey Chriſt the Son, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. vlt. Stumble not at his word, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. bee not offended at it, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6 60, 61, 67, 68, 69. heare Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.5. this great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.22, 23. and hee <hi>will giue the holy Ghost to them that obey him, Actes</hi> 5.32. The reiecting of the Word, is the reiecting of Chriſt, the receiuing of it, and his Miniſters, is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of Chriſt. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.21, and 13.20. 2. <hi>Theſſa.</hi> 1.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Abandon Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, Crucifixes, Relickes, <hi>Oralem manducationem:</hi> for by none of all theſe doe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1403:23"/> wee inioy Chriſt: which Idoles, the Deuill taking away the Word, and Goſpel, hath ſubſtituted in the roome to hold Chriſt by ſenſe, and not by Faith. Admit wee could receiue Chriſt by ſenſe, yea, and fill all our ſenſes with him; yet our ſoules could neuer bee ſaued by him, nor inioy his ſauing merites, and vertues, which can neuer come into the heart but by Faith, and <hi>the riches of the full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of vnderſtanding, in comprehending the myſterie of God the Father, and of Chriſt,</hi> which made <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching ſo <hi>full of agony and difficultie, Coloſ.</hi> 2.1, 2. which needed not if it were ſufficient to ſaluation, to communicate Chriſt to the ſenſes internall, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1403:23"/> But Chriſt is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed of the ſoule vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, onely of true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers through Faith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. who often haue leaſt feeling and fruition of him by ſenſe, and hee is often moſt taſted of Hypocrites by ſenſe, and felt by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts, who leaſt inioy him in their hearts by Faith of the Goſpel, and promiſes to ſaluation. It was an eaſie thing, for <hi>Paul</hi> to giue a taſt of Chriſt to the ſenſes, but it was his agonie as hee ſaith, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.1. and his child-bearing paines to forme Chriſt aright in their hearts, as <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. and ſo to giue their hearts ſound and ſauing comfort indeed, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.2.</p>
               <p>Hauing ſhewed that all ſauing good things in vs, are
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1403:24"/> ſauing vertues, in, and from Chriſt, and how, and by what meanes wee receiue &amp; draw theſe vertues from Chriſt, or inioy them in him. Now in the third place, we come to conſider theſe ſauing vertues in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, whereof here are two ſpecified, the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, which reſpect God as their obiect, and the ſtate of iuſtification before God, &amp; not ſo much our eſtate of ſanctification before men, and theſe are two, firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent acceſſe to God, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Manuduction, with confidence to God, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> boldneſſe of open face with libertie of ſpeach, for ſo much doeth the ſignification of the word import, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1403:24"/> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12, 13. and as ſhall further appeare in a larger vnfolding of the text in the next Sermon.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> this word im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports two things, firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to God, ſecondly the manner, by leading, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuduction, whereof I will ſpeake in the next Sermon.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> This the priuiledge of Gods Saints and people, they haue neere acceſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and into God by Faith; not onely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and contemplate of God a farre off, but their hearts &amp; ſoules draw neere <hi>to that light which none can attaine vnto,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.16.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Therefore the phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> not onely to beleeue God, or beleeue that there is a God, but by this faith to enter into God, <hi>to dwel in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1403:25"/> the ſecret of the moſt High,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and to abide vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the Almighty,</hi> to lodge in his boſome, and hide our ſelues with him, and <hi>vnder the ſhadow of his wings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 63.</note> to <hi>dwell in God, and God in vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.</note> that he <hi>keepes vs as the apple of his eye,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 17. Mat. 23.37.</note> and hee <hi>gathers vs as the Hen doeth her chickens vnder her wings.</hi> Hee beares vs as his Lambes in his boſome; the <hi>Name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 18.10.</note> 
                  <hi>the righteous runne to it, and into it, and are exalted:</hi> there is intimate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion betweene God and vs in our hearts, and ſoules. For in Chriſt his nature is fatherly to vs, not a conſuming fire, as to wicked men, and vnregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: He is the naturall ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a regenerate heart,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1403:25"/> and ſoule, wherein it liues, mooues, and workes all its workes in God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euery parent giues free acceſſe to its birth to come to it, and to hide its ſelfe in its boſome: how much more God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercies? This is our priuiledge by the Goſpel. In the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, none could ſo much as ſee God and liue; no man could warrant his heart to goe vnto God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> Make this thy onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge in all dangers, and troubles, hauing ſuch a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to flie vnto. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Aſhur ſhall not ſaue vs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will we ride vpon horſes, neither will wee ſay any more to the workes of our hands, Yee are our gods: for in thee the fatherleſſe findeth mercy.</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:1403:26"/> Thus ſaith euery true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, &amp; repentant ſoule, and this is the worke of Faith and of true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: If wee can call God Father, wee haue free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to him, and into his boſome, and vnder his armes wee may hide our ſelues with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This is our happineſſe that wee are not Orphans, but wee haue an euerliuing Father to flie and to runne vnto, and to hide our ſelues with him from all ſinnes, temptations, dangers, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, enemies. Wee need not flie from God, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God from all euills, euen our ſinnes to him, whom by ſinne we haue offended, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.19, 20, 21, 22. Count this thy onely hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, and reioyce in it.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:1403:26"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> How great is their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery that want this; If God bee ſhut vp againſt vs, all creatures are ſhut vp: wee are as <hi>Cain,</hi> runnagates vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the earth. If wee haue no acceſſe to God, whither ſhall we flie from his preſence, who is preſent in all places? All our ſinnes, and all euils, and miſeries finde vs out, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wee hide vs, if wee haue not him our Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, and inward Holy place to hide vs, as his ſecret ones, to abide vnder the protection of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Wee haue in God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, a ſecret hiding place, and Sanctuary to retire our ſelues vnto, where no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils ſinnes, enemies, croſſes, though they make hue and crie, and fierce purſuit af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1403:27"/> vs, as blood-Houndes, may bee able to finde vs. God hath ſuch a ſecret bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and hiding place for his children, ſuch a refuge and Sanctuary, whither Chriſt himſelfe is entred, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18, 19, 20. euen Ieſus our forerunner, and is now ſafe aboue the reach of all deuils, and men, <hi>and hath raiſed vs vp together, and made vs ſit together with him,</hi> in theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, moſt High, Heauenly places of refuge; <hi>our life is hid with Chriſt in God</hi> our Father, and neither <hi>famine, perill, ſword,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.35.39.</note> 
                  <hi>can ſeparate vs from the loue of God, in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This is for our great comfort, in all diſtreſſes, dangers, miſeries, when all creatures are ſhut vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1403:27"/> vs, and all wayes, and meanes of redemption, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, and deliuerance from enemies, and euils, if wee haue this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.20.</note> 
                  <hi>this new and liuing way made for vs, wee are ſafe;</hi> and contrary, if all creatures opened their boſome to entertaine vs, and the world loue vs, as her owne, and foſter vs: though nature ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all her children, and forces, to aide, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vs, ſo that wee could make our neaſtes in the ſtarres: yet if God bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, hee will plucke vs thence, he will hunt vs with blood-Hounds, and draw vs out with fiſhing hookes. Therefore repaire to God, and prepare thy place of refuge with him, againſt the euill day, acquaint thy
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1403:28"/> ſelfe with his boſome, and ſecret loue dayly, that it may bee thy preſent helpe in time of trouble, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to thee, and not locked and ſhut vp in time of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42, <hi>Hee is my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent helpe, and my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; In whom, that is, in Chriſt wee haue this acceſſe, and entrance to God, and Faith giues it, and workes it for vs, not in our ſelues, our workes, merites, righteouſneſſe, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the mediation of any Saint, or Angel: No crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can make way for vs to God, but Chriſt his Sonne <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Who died for ſinners, the iuſt for the vniuſt, that hee might bring vs to God. Iohn</hi> 14.6. <hi>I am the Way, the Trueth, and the Life: no
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1403:28"/> man commeth to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by me.</hi> No way to God, but Chriſt, no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to him, but by his Sonne. By Satan, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> wee were led out of the way, baniſhed, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from God, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill teaching, and leading vs a falſe way, how wee ſhould come to bee Gods, knowing good and euill, and ſo lead vs in the way of perdition, from God: this hee did by lies, and falſehood, deceiuing vs, and ſo killing vs, and euery ſin, like Satan, its parent, doeth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> draw vs out of the way from God, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> intiſe vs with promiſes of falſe comforts, profits, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſo kill vs. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.13, 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7 11. Now Chriſt, contrary to Satan,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1403:29"/> and to all ſinne, as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet hee teacheth vs the right way, and <hi>as a great high Priest of good things to come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9.11.</note> and ſuch as are truely good, and not onely hauing the ſhadowes of good things, hee giues vs true good things, by the word of trueth, which is the Goſpel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.11. with 10. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.17. <hi>This Law</hi> of ſhadowes was <hi>giuen by</hi> Moſes, <hi>but Grace and Trueth, comes by Ieſus Christ:</hi> and whereas Satan, and ſinne, kill by deceit, and raigne ouer vs by death; Chriſt as King, and Lord of life, quickens vs. No man in ſinne and Satan, could ſo much as ſee God, and liue: but now Chriſt, is both our way to God, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Prophet, the Trueth of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1403:29"/> all ſhadowes, and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Lawe, as true Prieſt, by whom wee goe to God, and as King, and Lord of life, wee liue by him. Hee is our light, as Prophet, to ſhew vs the way; hee is our Prieſt, to make the way to God; hee is our King, to make vs liue in Gods ſight, that we may not crie, as <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Hee ſhall reuiue vs, and wee ſhall liue in his ſight.</hi> This is our confident acceſſe to God, without feare, that the ſight, and preſence of God, ſhall not kill vs. All the workes, righteouſneſſe, and mediation of men and Angels, cannot make way for vs to God, but onely Chriſt his Sonne: Hee is the only way, and entrance to God.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:1403:30"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> For Gods loue, mercie, face, preſence, are ſhut vp from vs, and infinitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued from ſinners: yea, ſuch is the contrarietie of mans corrupt nature, to Gods infinite, pure, and holy nature, that it infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeparates, and remooues him from God,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.26.</note> 
                  <hi>by ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>haſma, or gulfe,</hi> that onely by ſuch a perſon, and high Prieſt, as is infinitely <hi>holy ſeparate from ſinners,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 7.22</note> 
                  <hi>and higher then the Heauens,</hi> can this gulfe bee filled vp, to make way to God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Chriſt first deſcended</hi> into the bottome of our hell,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.9.10</note> and miſerie, and from <hi>thence aſcended,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>farre aboue all things,</hi> that hee might bee our <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to bring many children vnto Glory, Heb.</hi> 2.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:1403:30"/>
               <p>For be we neuer ſo neere God, in place, Church, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, yea, and haue God in our mouthes, and could eate his reall fleſh; yet our hearts, and natures, are infinitly remooued, and ſeparated from God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt the Sonne of his boſome bring vs to him, and hee is Emanuel God with vs, ſo that <hi>now,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.39</note> 
                  <hi>neither height, nor depth, can ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vs,</hi> the Sonne of God, the ſecond perſon, hauing brought vs ſo neere to God. For no euill is ſo great a meanes of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs from God, as Chriſt is good, and a meanes to bring vs to God, the chiefe good. No euill of ſinne, or puniſhment ſo contrary, or remote from God, as Chriſt is neere to God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1403:31"/> with God, and one with God, and pleaſeth God, more then all ſinnes can diſpleaſe him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. vlt. <hi>My beloued Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 3.17. Iohn 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. <hi>The onely begotten Sonne, which is in the boſome of the Father, hee vnfolds God to vs,</hi> and makes vs neerer, and deerer to God: then ſinne which comes out of the boſome of the deuill, can make vs hatefull, and deteſtable to God, and this onely Chriſt can doe. To bring two ſuch contrary natures together, as light, and darkeneſſe, Gods infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite pure nature, and our fleſhly corrupt nature, muſt needes bee by an infinite meanes, of infinite merit, and vertue, God, and ſinne are ſo contrary.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:1403:31"/>
               <p>Therefore count all as doung, for Chriſt, to bring thee to God. Our wit, wealth, beauty, learning, righteouſneſſe, goodneſſe, may make way for vs to men, and Kings priuie-chambers, and to mens Thrones, and Courts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.1. But conſidered with our ſinnes, they are doung to God, and hee caſts vs, and all ours as dung out of doores, ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Hereby wee ſee the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, the glaſſe of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Law of God, and the glaſſe of the Goſpel. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. In the Law, and in Philoſophy this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is much moued, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of, what the chiefe good, and happineſſe of man is, and how it may bee
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1403:32"/> attained: but onely Faith in the glaſſe of the Goſpel, reſolues it fully. To ſee the face of God which is our life, and happineſſe, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Father of glory, and to attaine to this chiefe good, and by what way, and meanes to compaſſe him,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.25. Epheſ. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>is the myſtery hid from the foundation of the world.</hi> The creatures all crie, and profeſſe they are not the chiefe good, but point at God their Creator, and direct vs to him. The Law more cleerely ſhewes God to bee the chiefe good; but how we ſhould attaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him it ſhewes not, but but by a way impoſſible for fleſh to goe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. But the Goſpel doeth more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reueale God, as mans chiefe good, and ſhewes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1403:32"/> Chriſt to bee the onely way, and meanes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to him. Nature and Philoſophy, and all wit of man, is dimme, and weake in ſeeing, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding God the chiefe good; but its ſtarke blind to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the way, and meanes, whereby man, eſpecially a ſinner may come vnto God; <hi>This is that hid wiſedome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.7.9.</note> 
                  <hi>which God determined be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the worlds to our glory,</hi> which <hi>neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor euer entred into the heart of man, or Angel to conceiue,</hi> how once falling from God by ſinne, they ſhould euer bee able to recouer God againe, and come into fauour, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with him. For there is no way in nature, as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1403:33"/> by creation to God; all way is hedged and ſtopped vp by ſinne. All naturall good things, haue a naturall way prepared by creation, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be attained; but there is no way to attaine to that ſupernaturall chiefe good; <hi>its a light which cannot bee attained vnto.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16.</p>
               <p>The way is now prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by grace, that is Chriſt, the <hi>Sonne ſent</hi> from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note> not borne by nature, as a naturall way, <hi>but ſent</hi> from aboue as a <hi>Ladder</hi> reached vp to Heauen,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.12</note> Gods ſaluation <hi>which hee prepared before the face of all people.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 2.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.31.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> How is it then that wee are ſaid, <hi>to prepare the way, Matth.</hi> 3.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> Our preparation is for Chriſt, who is the way;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1403:33"/> Its not a way made by vs to God, but a fitting of our ſelues for Chriſt, who is the way, and that is as much as in vs lyeth, remoouing the things that hinder vs, that is our ſinnes by repentance, and by faith receiuing Chriſt. Not that repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Faith are our way, or any meanes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine God our chiefe good, but as preparations &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications for Chriſt, who is the only way and meanes of obtaining God. For faith of it ſelfe and Repentance, doe not iuſtifie vs, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vs to God, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vs for Chriſt to inioy, vſe and improoue him, in whom we walke as in the way to God, and eternall life and happineſſe. Faith and Repentance, and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:1403:34"/> good works are not worth a ruſh, nor haue any vertue to bring vs to God, but as they are from Chriſt, and doe vſe &amp; improoue Chriſt. By faith we receiue and chooſe Chriſt as the only way to God, forſaking all other waies, and meanes, and by repentance wee walke in Chriſt as in the way to God. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. <hi>As yee haue receiued Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Lord, ſo walke in him:</hi> ſo that neither Faith nor repentance are the way, but Chriſt. Therefore as yee haue receiued Chriſt by faith, as the way, ſo walke in this way by Repentance; that is, forſaking all ſinne and all meanes of ſafetie and lying vanities, make vſe of Chriſt Ieſus only for all ſauing good, <hi>Who is made
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1403:34"/> vnto vs of the Father, Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Righteouſneſſe, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, Redemption,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. For Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and all the works in the world without Chriſt cannot bring vs to God, and are of no worth with God, but as they make vſe and improouement of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> Let vs therefore care for nothing, but to get Chriſt, and let Chriſt be the End of our Faith and Workes, <hi>All our gaine and aduantage in life and death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> and then let Chriſt alone for brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vs to life, heauen and happineſſe. Let vs by Faith make way for Chriſt, to come into our hearts, to be our Prophet, Prieſt, King, Sheepheard, that we may receiue him, offering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1403:35"/> and then hee will make way for vs to God, to heauen and eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Let vs as ſheepe that goe aſtray daily, by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <hi>Conuert and returne to Chriſt the Sheepheard of our ſoules,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Acceſſe with confidence, or a confident acceſſe, not ſuch as was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law with feare and trembling, where the ſight was ſo terrible, that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, I feare and quake. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12, 13. with <hi>verſe</hi> 18, 19, 20.</p>
               <p>Wee come not before God as Diuels and Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors drawne into Gods preſence, as before the Iudge with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, to be arraigned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, inforced by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, nor yet as vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1403:35"/> beggers that roue and wander vp and downe for helpe, and knocke at euery doore, and ſo goe to Gods doore, but know not what intertainement they ſhall haue there. But wee haue good aſſurance, and good ſecuritie, and go confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in exſpectation of fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding good entertainment with God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12, 13. <hi>Lift vp your weake hands, and ſtrengthen your feeble knees and make ſtreight ſteps to your feete, least that which is halting be turned out of the way, &amp;c.</hi> As if he had ſaid; There is great danger and feare, we bee turned cleane out of the way, if we goe not confidently in the way. <hi>Prou.</hi> 18.10. <hi>The name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower, the righteous runneth to it,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1403:36"/> and is exalted. Running im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies confidence,</hi> Pſal. 33.6. <hi>They ſhall runne to him, and their faces ſhall not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This the property and vertue of this true Faith in Chriſt the Sonne of God our Mediatour, whereby we muſt prooue and trie it, and difference it from all faith in all creatures, and all meanes out of Chriſt, and all that affiance that man can haue in any naturall worldly helpes, that this Faith in Chriſt, ſteeles the heart, and ſtrengthens it with inuincible confidence, more then any faith in any religion or any creature in the world. It breeds <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a confident glorying and boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3.</note> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.20. <hi>Truſt in the Lord and ye ſhall be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.2.</note>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:1403:36"/> that is, your hearts ſhall be confident and free from thoſe feares, ſcruples, auxieties, whereby carnall men that truſt in earthly things,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.29.</note> 
                  <hi>hang in ſuſpence like Meteors in the aire,</hi> waſting themſelues and their liues, with continual cares, feares, and griefes, and are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.6, 7, 8. running from one helpe to another, and are neuer ſecure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.14. <hi>Be ſtrong and he ſhall ſtrengthen your heart, that is, ſeeke all your ſtrength</hi> and ſafetie by faith in God, and not in earthly things, and God ſhall ſtrengthen your hearts with confidence. No faith breeds <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but this, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.4. that is full certainty, and <hi>Act.</hi> 2.36. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.1. All other refuges that men flye vnto, are with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1403:37"/> doubting, anxiety, and ſome diſtruſt whether our workes, or mediation of Saints or Angels, or any creature, becauſe both the refuges themſelues are not ſure, nor cannot promiſe certaine &amp; infallible helpe, and therefore can giue no full ſecuritie to the minde; but God is a moſt ſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible and impregnable defence and ſtrong tower, and therefore the righteous runne to it with full confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: or ſecondly, the meanes, that men vſe to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thereto may faile them, and therefore they vſe them not without care, feare, anxiety; but Chriſt is a moſt ſure and infallible meanes to bring vs to God, and cannot faile, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Faith in him
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1403:37"/> breeds that confidence, That as God is a ſure ſtrong and vndoubted defence, that no man can make que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: So is Chriſt his Son like him, as ſure a Meane and Mediatour to come to him, and to obtaine him.</p>
               <p>But of this vertue of Faith, and how its increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and confirmed in Chriſt the obiect, ſhall appeare more in the next Sermon.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, boldneſſe of face and freedome of ſpeech. Of all the vertues of Chriſt, which he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in our hearts, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 3.3.</note> this is one of <hi>the chiefe, that he is the lifter vp of our heads, and exalts</hi> our faces before God, and giues vs free liberty of ſpeech to plead with God, that wee poore ſinners, duſt and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1403:38"/> aſhes may pleade and parle with God, and ſtand vpon interrogatories with him, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. <hi>The interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory which a good conſcience makes to God.</hi> For the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience beeing acquitted from the guilt of ſinne, by the ſprinkling of the blood of Chriſt, is made bold to queſtion with God, and to aske him what hee hath more to lay to our charge: What more full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſatisfaction his Iuſtice can require, then what Chriſt hath already made. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Come let vs reaſon together.</hi> 2. Cor. 7.11. <hi>We can make our</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>cleere our ſelues before God,</hi> for whatſoeuer can be laid to our charge; and cry <hi>Abba</hi> Father, and poure out our hearts before him in all our
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1403:38"/> afflictions, and bemoane our ſelues to God, and all our wrongs, croſſes, indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. For Chriſt hauing ſtopped the mouth of the Law, and of all iniquitie, and of our crying ſinnes, which ſtopped our mouths, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.42. thereby opens our mouth to God. <hi>Dauid</hi> vpon the guilt of murther and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery had his mouth ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and gagged, and euery man by the Law and ſpirit of bondage, hath his mouth ſealed vp: let Chriſts ſpirit open it, by the ſprinkling and waſhing of the blood of Chriſt, applyed by faith, and then vpon experience of Gods free ſauing grace and mercy, pardoning and healing the guilt of his ſin, his mouth was opened,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1403:39"/> that his lippes might ſet forth the praiſe of this his ſauing grace, loue &amp; mercy.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is the Lyon of the tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and courage with God is his naturall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar vertue, and which he dwelling in our hearts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſeth in vs, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he is now riſen from the dead, and ſits at the right hand of God, making interceſſion for vs. For whatſoeuer Chriſt is in Heauen, or doth for vs there, he is the ſame in our hearts, and the vertue and influence of it deſcends in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, and <hi>raiſeth vs vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 2.6.</note> 
                  <hi>and makes vs ſit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with him in the heauenly places;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and Chriſt dwelles in vs vertually,</hi> as he doth in heauen, yea Chriſt riſen from the dead
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1403:39"/> and making interceſſion for vs in heauen, and liuing there for vs, is the ſame Chriſt in our hearts, and in the temple of our ſoules, and conſciences, as he is in heauen, the ſame perſon, exerciſing the ſame office and vertues in the inner holy place of our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences before God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into he is entred by his blood, and hath made way for himſelfe to raigne in vs, as King of <hi>Salem</hi> &amp; Prince of Peace, as hee doth in heauen for vs. For God is in the Sanctuary of our conſciences, being purged by the blood of his Sonne, as he is in heauen his holy place, our ſoules beeing made and framed like to heauen to be Gods Houſe and Temple. The <hi>Fabricke</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:1403:40"/> of the Iewiſh Temple, was not only a type of heauen, but of our ſoules the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of God, and therefore Chriſt is our High Prieſt and doth his office o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prieſt-hood as well in our ſoules as in heauen, and as <hi>A Miniſter of the true Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bernacle which God pitch and not man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 8.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>As by his blood he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <hi>as by a new and liuing way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.20</note> 
                  <hi>into the Sanctuary o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> heauen,</hi> ſo doth he enter in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to our conſciences: and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he makes interceſſion, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeakes for vs in heauen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth he in our hearts wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">1. Pet 3.21.</note> the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogatory which a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience makes to God by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Reſurrection of Ieſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> from the dead,</hi> or Chriſt r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen vp in it, with that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:1403:40"/> and <hi>that Spirit which</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>makes requeſt for the Saints.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> Chriſt was arraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, accuſed, condemned for our ſinnes, and he ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and anſwered for all, that we alſo in him might anſwer for our ſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Highly prize this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. We that could not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer God, for one of a thouſand, now can anſwer all inditements and obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by Chriſt. Wee that could not abide the leaſt triall, nor indure the leaſt ſearch, can now abide the moſt ſeuere Iudgement and moſt exquiſite triall, <hi>being found in Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>not hauing our owne righteouſneſſe, but his righteouſneſſe.</hi> Elſe, <hi>if thou ſtreightly marke what is done amiſſe, who is able to abide it? Pſal.</hi> 130.3.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:1403:41"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Let vs prooue our ſelues how Chriſt is in vs. How doth he open our mouthes to God? If Chriſt be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, in the heart, hee opens the mouth, as a Prieſt to God. What new opening of thy mouth, before ſeale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſtopped vp by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Law? The guilt of ſinne makes ſpeechleſſe &amp; dumb as <hi>Zachary.</hi> Infidelity make dumbe; but as ſoone as by faith we receiue Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts, he opens ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mouthes to pray, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before we could neuer doe Chriſt giues a new mout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and tongue, not only t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeake to men, but to God not only to pleade our e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uill righteouſneſſe in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> courts of men, but in God courts, and to ſtand vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> interrogatories with him
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1403:41"/> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.1. If <hi>Abraham be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by workes, he hath to glory, but not with God;</hi> He may ſtand and pleade his righteouſneſſe boldly, in mens courts, but not in Gods. But we can pleade in heauen, and make our Appeale to the Throne of Grace, and there make our Apologie,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.2.</note> and <hi>Take to vs words, and ſay, Receiue vs graciouſly, ſo will we render the calues of our lippes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ye are carefull ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. <hi>To prooue and try your Ministers, yee will haue experience of Christ ſpeaking in me;</hi> Its well,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13 3.5.</note> but withall <hi>prooue your ſelues whether Chriſt bee in you.</hi> Know that <hi>the ſame Chriſt, and ſo his ſpirit that ſpeakes in me, and opens my mouth to ſpeake from God to you,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1403:42"/> enters</hi> into your hearts, and opens your mouthes freely to ſpeake to God. Hereby we may know if we heare the word ſauing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and receiue Chriſt by Faith. Therefore not only prooue and try your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whether Chriſt ſpeak and preach in them, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo try your ſelues whether ye be in the Faith, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Chriſt, to ſpeake to God in prayer, elſe ye are not fit nor able to iudge whether Chriſt ſpeake in me. Such a ſpirit of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as opens the Miniſters mouth to ſpeake from Chriſt to the people, ſuch a ſpirit enters into the people and Church by Faith, in the word heard, and opens the mouthes of the people to pray. Prayer
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1403:42"/> is a common gift of euery member of the Church. <hi>Euery one must call on the Name of the Lord that will be ſaued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Rom. 10.13, 14, 15.</note> though euery one muſt not preach. Firſt, the Miniſters mouth muſt be opened to preach, before the peoples mouthes can be opened to pray. To put downe a preaching Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery vnder colour of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp a praying Miniſtery is by ſinfull Hypocriſie, to put downe both; and to deuoure not only wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes houſes, but the houſe of God vnder colour of long prayer, as the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees then did, and Papiſts now doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:1403:43"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>EPHES. 3.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>In whom we haue boldneſſe and acceſſe, with confidence by the faith of him.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THere are two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall radicall and fundamentall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in a Chriſtian heart and inward man, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith and Repentance, <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 6.2. <hi>Repentance from dead Workes, and Faith towards God.</hi> Theſe two rootes ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by fruits in life and conuerſation. Repentance ſhewes it ſelfe in hating and flying ſinne, and in vſing all meanes of abſtaining from
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1403:43"/> ſinne and vanities. Faith ſhewes it ſelfe in motions and imployments towards God, which are chiefely theſe two.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our Acceſſe to God by Manuduction, as led by Chriſt, which makes vs confident in going to God, becauſe we are led, and goe not of our ſelues. As with all care and feare, we flie all ſinne by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; ſo we muſt boldly and confidently goe to God, being led by Chriſt taking vs by the hand.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond motion or imployment, is free<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of ſpeech.</p>
               <p>The firſt is of the inner man, the ſecond of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man.</p>
               <p>The worke and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Faith in the ſoule
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1403:44"/> called that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by which we moſt ſerue, honour and attend on God, as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.3. ſtands in theſe things here ſet downe in this <hi>verſe.</hi> 1. We take Chriſt our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour by the hand, and lay hold on him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, that faith which laies hold on his Perſon. 2. Hauing him by the hand, and led by him to God, we haue acceſſe to God, &amp; goe to him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3. We goe with boldneſſe and confidence being ſo led, and hauing ſuch a guide, as the ſecond Perſon in Trinitie, the Sonne of God. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 4. Beeing come to God in this confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, led by Chriſt, we open our minds, and hearts, and ſpeake to him freely
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1403:44"/> with open face without feare or ſhame. Of theſe in their order.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Faith laies hold on Chriſts Perſon, and takes him by the hand in all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to God, and in all things wherein we haue to doe with God. We muſt haue nothing to doe with God, without Chriſt our Mediatour. As the Iewes had no dealings with God, no acceſſe to him, but by the high Prieſt <hi>taken from among men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and ordained for men in all things appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to God;</hi> Therefore they firſt went to the high Prieſt, before they went to God. So we muſt firſt goe to Chriſt, before we goe to God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. The ſoule cannot thinke of going to God, but
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1403:45"/> it thinkes of laying hold of ſomewhat, by which to be imboldned to goe vnto God, to finde acceptance with him. Therfore it ſaith to it ſelfe;<note place="margin">Mich. 6.6, 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Wherewith ſhall I come before the Lord, and bow my ſelfe before the high God?</hi> who, or what ſhall warrant me, a worme, duſt and aſhes, to goe to ſo high and a great God? <hi>Reaſon and fleſh ſaith</hi> 10005. <hi>of rammes, and ten thouſand and fiue ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of oyle, and ſome great thing</hi> anſwerable to ſo great a God. No man can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the Highneſſe and Greatneſſe of God aboue himſelfe, and thinke of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, but he muſt alſo thinke of what hee muſt bring to God.</p>
               <p>But Faith, as it only ſees aright the height and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1403:45"/> of the moſt High God, and the face of tha Father of glory, in the glaſſe of the Goſpel, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo hee hath reuealed and offered vs a Mediatour, anſwerable to himſelfe, and to his glory: ſo faith onely anſweres this queſtion, and reſolues the ſoule, ſaying, <hi>Hee hath ſhewed thee O man, what is good, and what the Lord requires of thee;</hi> There is nothing great, and good enough for God, but Chriſt his Sonne: He is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely abaſed, if any thing neuer ſo great, or good, bee thought fit to preſent to God, or to warrant vs to goe to him, but onely Chriſt his Son. Eſpecially we thinke too baſely of his Maieſtie and Glory, if wee conceiue that the ſame
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1403:46"/> offended by ſinne, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured, can bee ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by any creature, but by his onely Sonne, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon in Trinity, and <hi>ſhall wee thinke to giue the fruit of our body, for the ſinne of our ſoule!</hi> No, its onely the fruit of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines wombe, that Branch, and Off-ſpring of <hi>Dauid,</hi> the onely begotten Sonne of God.</p>
               <p>Now Faith, firſt laies holde on the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt, as a handle fit for mans nature, to lay ſure hold on: and as the hand of the Sonne of God, fit for vs to grapple, or graſpe, and imbrace as our owne fleſh. For it cannot lay hold on the God-head; its fire conſuming; in the man-hood it imbraceth the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1403:46"/> 
                  <hi>God-head, dwelling in it bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily. Coloſ.</hi> 2.9. As he that holds a Lanthorne by the handle, receiues, and holds alſo the light thit is in the Lanthorne: So he that by Faith laies hold on Chriſts fleſh, and body, as the Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne, laies hold on Chriſt the ſecond Perſon, and the fulneſſe of the God-head, and <hi>hee is Emanuel God with him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> In going to God, ſome lay hold on their workes, as the Phariſie, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. ſome on Saints and Angels, as the Papiſts: let vs onely lay hold on Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">2. Heb. 2, &amp;c. 12.2.</note> hauing hold on Chriſt, he goes before, and leads, and wee follow him, as our <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and our fore-runner, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18, 19, 20. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. <hi>We were
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1403:47"/> as ſheepe that went aſtray, following our lusts, but now are returned to the Shep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heard of our ſoules,</hi> that hee may lead vs to God. Its nothing, what ſinnes wee turne from, if we turne not to Chriſt, to leade vs to God, the chiefe good; its nothing, what euils wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid, if we goe not ſtreight to God, and make ſtraight ſteps to our feet. This lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the hand, is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as a <hi>Medium,</hi> or middle vertue, or motion, to two extreames.</p>
               <p>Firſt deſperation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Deuils, and wicked Men flie from God, and come not to him, but as drawne, and compelled, and that with horrour, and hatred of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, preſumption
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1403:47"/> of proud, and blind Iuſtitia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries, that goe to God of themſelues, as the Phariſie, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. not led by the hand of a Mediatour, but truſting to themſelues. As Sathan leades all wicked mens ſoules to Hell, ſo Chriſt leades the ſoules of all Saints to God. That is called the Spirit of the world, which ſwayes the whole world, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. this the Spirit of Chriſt, ſwaying all his body, and members.</p>
               <p>Hee onely leads vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee onely remooues whatſoeuer makes vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, or vnfit to come, or feares, and diſcourageth vs to come vnto God, and giues vs whatſoeuer makes vs acceptable, as his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, merits, ſacrifice, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:1403:48"/>
               <p>Hee came downe from the boſome of the Father, to bring vs thither, and was made fleſh for this end, that by the hand of his fleſh, wee might lay hold on him crucified, and riſen againe, and ſo be drawne by him to God. He is that ladder of aſcenſion to God. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Shall wee not then goe to Chriſt, who is come downe from Heauen to vs, and ſuffer our ſelues to bee led by him, and drawne from the world, but follow our reaſon, and luſts, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing earthly vanities? ſhall wee be ſtill as ſheepe that ſtray, and not come to the Shepheard of our ſoules, that hee may leade vs to God, who hath died for vs, to make way for vs, by
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:1403:48"/> his blood to God, and is riſen from the dead, for this end, to bee our Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, and is gone the way before vs? <hi>To vs hath God raiſed vp his Sonne Ieſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 3. verſ. laſt.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſent him to bleſſe vs, in turning euery one of vs from our iniquities, Actes</hi> 3. vlt. <hi>He is raiſed vp to vs of God, and giuen vs to be a Prince, and a Sauiour, to giue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to Iſrael, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of Sinnes. Actes</hi> 5.31.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The woefull condition of ſuch as are without Chriſt, <hi>they are without hope,</hi> and <hi>without God in the world, Epheſ.</hi> 2. and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all hope, of euer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to God. <hi>He that obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Sonne,</hi> to follow him, and to bee led, and guided by him, <hi>ſhall not ſee
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1403:49"/> life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.36.</note> 
                  <hi>but the wrath of God abideth on him; but he that beleeueth in the Sonne,</hi> to follow him as his Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, and his voyce, and doctrine, as <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. <hi>hath euerlasting life. My ſheepe heare my voyce, and I know them, and I giue vnto them eternall life.</hi> ſee 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10. <hi>Becauſe they obeyed not the Goſpel of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> to bee led, and guided by him, the Prince of their ſaluation, but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed their owne reaſon, and luſts, and ſenſes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3. Iohn 14.6.</note>Therefore commit thy ſelfe to Chriſt, to bee thy guide, to walke by him as the way, to bee counſelled, and led by him as the trueth, and quickned, and ſtrengthened by him as the life; and neuer doubt, but
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1403:49"/> he will bring thee to God ſafely, and thou ſhalt neuer miſcarie. Hee will bring thee into his reſt, and where God dwels, and preſent thee before his face, and <hi>perfectly ſaue thee. Heb.</hi> 7.25. Thou ſhalt neuer periſh by any ſinnes, luſts, temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, croſſes, miſeries; for Chriſt hath made the way ſafe through all theſe, and leade the way by ſinnes, temptations, death, <hi>to make it</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a liuing way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.20 1. Pet. 2.24</note> 
                  <hi>bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all our ſinnes in his body on the Tree, who in that hee ſuffered, &amp; was tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</hi> Therefore onely commit thy minde, and heart, to bee guided by him, truſting to him as thy Prophet to counſell thee, and call none Rabbi but
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:1403:50"/> him: thy onely Prieſt, to lead thee to God, &amp; king to defend and to quicken thee. Renounce thy reaſon, wit, learning, luſts, and all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, truſting to Chriſt thy Shepheard onely, to bring thee out of Egypt, of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans bondage, and darkenes, and to leade thee through the wildernes of this world. For onely the Sonne that came from God his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, can bring vs to God, <hi>commit thy way vnto the Lord, and thy thoughts ſhall be directed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee as the Shepheard of of thy ſoule,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.18.</note> will <hi>keepe thee from euery euill worke,</hi> nor ſuffer Satan, or luſt, or the world, to withdraw thee from God.<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.21.</note> 
                  <hi>When thou tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to the right hand, or to the left, thou ſhalt heare a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:1403:50"/> voyce behind thee, ſaying, This is the way, walke in it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>He is thy ſhepheard, and hee will conuert thy ſoule, when it goes aſtray:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee will make vs wiſe to ſaluation, againſt the deceits of ſinne,</hi> and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vanities; <hi>Hee that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes him ſhall not walke in darkeneſſe, but ſhall haue the light of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Say not in thy heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>who ſhall aſcend to Heauen, or who ſhall deſcend into the deepe to goe to God!</hi> For Chriſt is come from aboue to bring vs to God, and hee is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended into the loweſt deepes, to draw vs out from thence to God, <hi>ſo that neither height,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.39.</note> 
                  <hi>nor depth, can ſeparate vs from God.</hi> Bee God neuer ſo high aboue vs, and wee ſuncke neuer ſo low in hell,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1403:51"/> and miſery belowe him, euen to the bottome of hell; Chriſt is come from aboue, to cary vs vp aboue, and hee is deſcended into the loweſt depths of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to fetch and draw forth the moſt miſerable, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt them to Heauen, and to bring them to God. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither famine, perill, ſword,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>height, or depth, can ſeparate vs from the loue of God in Chriſt,</hi> but Chriſt will bring vs to God, if we make him our Shepheard, and lay hold on him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Hang and depend not on any man, or creature, <hi>Say not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>I am</hi> Pauls, <hi>I am</hi> Apollos, Chriſt is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhepheard of our ſoules. Say not, what Saint, or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ſhall lead mee to God? <hi>Was</hi> Paul <hi>crucified for vs?</hi> or
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:1403:51"/> did <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or any Saint, or Angel come downe from Heauen, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend into Hell, and come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead againe, to lead vs to God? <hi>God dwels in that light inacceſsible,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.18.</note> 
                  <hi>which no man, or Angel can come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> but onely Chriſt to lead vs to God, to ſee his Face, and to inioy his preſence. By other meanes &amp; guides, wee may bee brought to wealth, glory, honour, health, as by learning, loue, workes of righteouſneſſe, Philoſophy: but neuer come to God, to ſee and inioy him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Hereby wee may know the true Faith, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and whether Chriſt and his ſpirit bee in vs. If they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rie vs out of our ſelues, and from all creatures to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1403:52"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:1403:52"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:1403:53"/> God, to ſeeke all life, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, glory, ſtrength, and ſafetie in God, and not in our ſelues, or any creature, that <hi>there bee not in any of vs an euill heart of infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3.12. verſe 14.</note> 
                  <hi>to depart away from the liuing God; Then are wee partakers of Chriſt, if wee hold that</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that principall pillar of ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> and the foundation of our ſuſtentation, which is God our Rocke, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donay</hi> our ſtaies; For ſo I vnderſtand that place.</p>
               <p>Conſider how thou commeſt before God, in prayer, and in his Church: how is it, thou dareſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in his preſence, and tread in his Courts, who makes way for thee, and leades thee? There is a third fleſhly boldnes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:1403:53"/> by many ruſh into the Lords houſe, and to his Table, which makes them more bold then welcome, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.12, 13. who being not led by Chriſt, when hee ſhall queſtion with them, and ſay,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Friend how cameſt thou in hither, not hauing me for thy guide?</hi> they will become <hi>ſpeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi> ouerwhelmed with the more deſperate hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as they came in with the more boldneſſe. They are moſt bould to goe to God, who haue the leaſt grounds of true boldneſſe, and theſe haue moſt feare in the end. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14. If Chriſt make way for thee, then bee as bould, as thou wilt. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.14, 15, 16, &amp; chap. 10.19.22.</p>
               <p>In this Manuduction, or
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:1403:54"/> leading to God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> wee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two things. Firſt the ground of it. Secondly the maner, and meanes. The ground is feare, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which by this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuduction is healed, that wee may goe to God with boldneſſe, and confidence. There bee two things, that make boldneſſe, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and the contrary makes feare, and diffidence. Firſt affinitie of nature. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly familiaritie, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance: the firſt is the cauſe of the latter. The corruption, and contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our nature, and our eſtrangement, and vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God, by dayly defection from him by actuall ſinne, makes vs feare, and diſtruſt God, and therefore cannot, nor dare
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:1403:54"/> not goe to God by our ſelues, but wee muſt be led by ſuch a one, as is of the ſame infinite, Holy, and perfect nature with God, and neuer departed from him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but <hi>lies alwayes in his boſome,</hi> who leading vs by the hand, wee haue bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards God.</p>
               <p>For that wee may bee bould, and confident with God: Firſt our hearts, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and conſciences muſt bee purged, from all that which is contrary to God, and made of Gods nature. Secondly, wee muſt haue perfect acquaintance with God, as lying in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; neither of which haue wee in our ſelues, and in our owne perſons, but in the <hi>perſon of Chriſt, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in our hearts by Faith,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1403:55"/> Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. and by putting on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, we haue both: firſt our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are purged from all that which is contrary to God, as the guilt of ſinne, as <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10. <hi>Draw neere with a true heart, in aſſurance of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Faith firſt purgeth the heart, and by that purgation after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth its owne aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the heart.</note>Firſt, a true heart pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and ſanctified, and then followes aſſurance of faith. But what makes a true heart, and like to God? He ſhewes its one by two things. Firſt <hi>ſprinckled with the blood of Chriſt,</hi> to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and Chriſt dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in it. Secondly, <hi>waſhed in our bodies with pure wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of ſanctification, begun in it. As the ſtrongeſt, and ſtouteſt creatures are afraid of thoſe things, which are contrary to their natures,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:1403:55"/> which other creatures ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo weake feare not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame nature. No more fearefull creature then a fiſh, flying at the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a man; yet it feares not the Ocean ſea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe its of its owne nature, which Lyons, and the ſtou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt creatures feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Acquaintance, and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie with God. A ſheepe feares not his Shepheard, by reaſon of acquaintance, whom yet the Beare, and the Wolfe feare: whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is ſtrange, and vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, is fearefull. If we acquaint our ſelues with God, and walke with him as his friends, we ſhall haue the more bouldneſſe with God:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.8.</note> 
                  <hi>elſe hee meetes vs as a Beare robbed of her whelps, and as a Lyon in ſecret places.</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:1403:56"/> In whom both theſe are wholly wanting, as in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, and all wicked men, there is no acceſſe to God, no acquaintance, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, as in all of vs by nature, wee are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lients from God, and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the wombe, and goe aſtray, and can neuer come where God is. In whom theſe are imperfect, as in the regenerate; that nature is partly renewed, and fellowſhip, &amp; acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God in part, to know God by repentance; but in part through contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie, and corruption of nature, and defection from God dayly by actuall ſins, there is no immediate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to God, but by a Mediatour, leading by the hand: as among men that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:1403:56"/> are ſtrangers, though of the ſame nature. In this mixt condition, there is a mixt motion of acceſſe to God, which is by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuduction of a Mediatour, of perfect nature, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate fellowſhippe with God. If in our owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons wee were perfectly holy, and like vnto God in our nature, and had full, and perfect acquaintance with God, neuer departing from him, nor eſtranged by any ſinne; then wee might goe to God of our ſelues, and needed not a Mediatour, to take vs by the hand.</p>
               <p>Againe, haue wee neuer ſo much corruption of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if there bee any true grace, and ſparke of Gods nature, and life in vs, wee need not feare, and runne
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:1403:57"/> away from God, as long as wee haue a Mediatour, to take vs by the hand, who will not deſpiſe, <hi>nor quench the ſmoaking flaxe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>nor breake the bruiſed reede,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>but with one offering hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected for euer, them that are ſanctified,</hi> in any ſmall meaſure. And though we dayly fall from fellowſhip with God by ſinnes, yet if there bee any conſtant will, and deſire of repentance, and ſeedes of conuerſion, &amp; acquaintance with God, and that wee hate not fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with God, as the Deuils, and flie from him, (as they are not capable of a Mediatour, by ſuch a contrariety, to lead them, neither are ſuch their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.) We are capable of a Mediatour, to bring vs into
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:1403:57"/> perfect fellowſhippe with God, and of ſuch a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard to leade vs, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert vs. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.1, 2. God in himſelfe is full, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect light,<note place="margin">See 1. Ioh. 1 5.10. with chap. 2.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and in him is no darkeneſſe at all:</hi> Wee by nature are nothing but darkeneſſe, and in vs is no light at all.</p>
               <p>Now comes Chriſt a Mediatour betweene vs both, that becauſe there can be no communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene light, and darkneſſe, Chriſt the middle perſon in Trinitie, becomes a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle perſon alſo betweene God and vs, by taking our fleſh; betweene God that ſimple light, and vs that are nothing but darkeneſſe, &amp; communicating of both our natures, and taking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him all our ſinnes, brings
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:1403:58"/> vs into fellowſhippe with God, reconciling, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the enmitie betweene God and vs in iuſtification, and then imparting Gods nature in part, in ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which becauſe its imperfect, by his perfect ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and interceſſion, and leading to God dayly, hee reneweth, and increaſeth our fellowſhip with God, and communion, till we be preſented perfect in Chriſt Ieſus, to God his Father. According therfore to our mixt condition in this life of light, and darkeneſſe, holineſſe, and corruption, wee haue a mixt acceſſe to God, which is by Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</p>
               <p>Hence ariſe theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſectaries. Firſt, wee muſt haue ſinne, corruption of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:1403:58"/> nature, contrarietie and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie to God in nature, and life, and often fall from God by daily ſinnes; elſe we needed not a Mediator. We might goe to God of our ſelues. Secondly, We haue neede of ſuch and ſo great a Mediatour to lead vs to God, as is holy, harmeleſſe, ſeparate from ſinners, and made higher then the heauens, becauſe the curſed enmity of our natures, and eſtrangement from God, ſo requires it, and needs it. None other can lead ſuch wicked ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to God, ſo full of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and abhomination in nature and life, to ſo iuſt and holy a God, but ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite holy Sonne of God. Thirdly, If there be any ſparke of God and Chriſts
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:1403:59"/> nature and life in vs, its ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make vs capable of ſuch a Mediatour, to take vs by the hand as his brethren, partakers of his fleſh &amp; blood, to bring vs to God his Father. Fourthly, Such as haue no loue to God, nor fellowſhip with Chriſt by repentance, but loue darkeneſſe rather then light, and fellowſhip with ſinne and Satan, haue in this eſtate no benefite of this Mediatour.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Hereby we ſee, what it is to be a Puritan. To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe or thinke himſelfe to be ſo holy of himſelfe, as daring to goe to God in his owne name, that he needs not a Mediatour to lead him; that feeles no ſuch filth and corruption in himſelfe, for which God
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:1403:59"/> ſhould abhorre him: or if there be ſinne, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet its ſo little, light, and veniall, that we neede not make ſo great friends and ſuite, a Saint or Angel may be ſufficient for media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Such a Puritane was the proud Phariſee, and euery carnall preſumptuous Atheiſt, who without faith and repentance dare goe to God in the Church, to the Word and Sacraments, and ſuch as goe in confidence of their ceremoniall righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. Theſe lay the imputation of Puritaniſme on others, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues chiefely practiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Sinne being an infinite euill, and infinitely hated of God, its infinite pride and preſumption for any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to dare to preſent ſuch
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:1403:60"/> a ſinner to God. For its worſe then any ſinne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt God, to be an Aduocate for ſinners, to dare to ſpeake for them, and to countenance them before God, as <hi>Romanes</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> laſt. vnleſſe that hee that ſhall dare to doe this, be as great as God, and as a ſurety will vndertake to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie and anſwer God for them: and therfore to make any Saint a Mediatour to God for ſinners, is to make him God. So much of the Ground of this lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>In the Meanes and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of leading, we conſider. Firſt, the Perſon leading. Secondly, the Perſons led. Thirdly, the hands by which the one leadeth, and the other is led.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:1403:60"/>
               <p>The Perſon leading, as I haue ſhewed, is only the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Perſon in Trinitie the Sonne of God, made fleſh like vnto vs, as I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhewed.</p>
               <p>The Perſons led, are the Saints and children of God, reconciled by Chriſts fleſh crucified, and imperfectly ſanctified as is alſo ſhewed. The hands by which this leading is made, are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and diſtinctly to bee conſidered. And firſt the hand of Chriſt the Perſon leading.</p>
               <p>The hand of the ſecond Perſon in Trinitie Ieſus Chriſt, euen now as he is man, is his ſpirit. As it was the hand of the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before hee was made Fleſh, ſo it is now ſince he is made Fleſh, eſpecially
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:1403:61"/> ſince his Reſurrection. The hand of God is the hand alſo of Fleſh, now riſen from the dead, and glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now God hath no hand but his Spirit; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Sonne haue no hands but the Spirit the holy Ghoſt. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can proceed from the Father and the Sonne, but the holy Ghoſt, which is ſometimes called the hands of God: Thy hands haue made mee and faſhioned me, that is, as elſe-where is expounded, his Spirit, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.5. <hi>Who knoweth the way of the Spirit, and how the bones grow in the wombe of her that is with childe?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 26.13.</note> 
                  <hi>His Spirit garniſhed the heauens,</hi> and renueth the Face of the Earth;<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſendeſt forth thy Spirit, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:1403:61"/> they are created,</hi> which in other places is called his hands: <hi>His hands prepared the dry land;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 101.26.</note> And <hi>Chriſt calles it the finger of God; If I by the finger of God cast out Diuels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 11.20.</note> 
                  <hi>then is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God come vnto you,</hi> which is expounded by him to be his Spirit. Its al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo called the breath of God which proceeds from him; the heauens were made by the word of the Lord, and all the Hoſt of them by the breath of his mouth; and His word and Spirit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede and come forth from him together: that is, his commandement and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite diuine Spirit and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as his Arme, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its called the Word of his power, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. Who hath beleeued our report,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:1403:62"/> and to whom is the Arme of the Lord reuealed? and the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed forth by his Spirit. Its called the ſhadow of God, and the wings of God, and whatſoeuer proceeds from the Father and the Son, to Man or to any creature, is only the holy Spirit. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.35. <hi>The holy Ghoſt ſhall come vpon thee, and the power of the moſt High ſhall ouer ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.1.</note> Pſal. 90.1. <hi>Such as dwell in the ſecret of the most High ſhall abide vnder the ſhadow of the Almightie.</hi> Pſal. 63. <hi>Vnder the ſhadow of thy wings, will I reioyce;</hi> all which muſt be meant of his Spirit, counſelling, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting, ſtrengthning, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.1. Woe bee to them that ſeeke a couering, and not by my Spirit. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:1403:62"/> 
                  <hi>Mary</hi> conceiuing by the holy Ghoſt, without all power of nature, a weake woman, ſings,<note place="margin">Luke 2.</note> 
                  <hi>that God had ſhewed ſtrength with his Arme.</hi> As the ſhadow comes from the body, ſo the holy Ghoſt from God, which is therefore ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times called a ſhadow, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſhewes it ſelfe but darkely, obſcurely, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically, and yet ſurely and powerfully, and this eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Miniſtry of the Church, both in Miniſters and people. In Miniſters, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.16. <hi>I haue hid thee vnder the ſhadow of my hand, that I may plant the heauens, &amp;c.</hi> that is, I will powerfully by my Spirit way thee, and inable to this ſo great a worke, as to make a new world by thee,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:1403:63"/> and protect thee from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels and men. No ſhadow can proceede from God, but what is God himſelfe, his Spirit and Diuine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and vertue, which when its giuen obſcurely, and not ſo manifeſtly, is called a ſhadow. In people as <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. that is, when God in his infinite loue, mercy and grace, ſhining to you as his face, ſhall ſend to you his Spirit, the Comforter, which ſhall aſſure you of the pardon of your ſinnes, and refreſh you with ioy, peace, comfort in Chriſts righteouſneſſe applied to you, blotting out your ſins out of your conſciences, if ye continue to grieue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and to be ſorrowfull for them daily, and by ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to kill and mortifie
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:1403:63"/> them. Let all your care be only to repent, and to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment your ſinnes, to morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, and to grieue for them all your dayes, and God knowes the beſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon when to refreſh you with comfort, which is the Seaſon of all Seaſons, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, when to giue you the Spirit the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as an infinite gift of his Fatherly loue and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and when to ſhew you that his Fatherly Face, and the refreſhing from it, by ſending his holy Spirit to aſſure your grieued hearts of his fauour, and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled in Chriſt, which is the moſt comfortable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing ſeaſon, that can come to a mans ſoule. Now we muſt not appoint God this ſeaſon, when to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:1403:64"/> refreſh vs, with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of his Face, and Loue by his Spirit; but we muſt goe on in our worke, and labour of repentance, and daily turning to God flying all ſins, and vſing all meanes of obtaining all the good promiſed vs, and God in his due time, after all our toile, labour, and ſorrowes, will ſend his Spirit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh vs.</p>
               <p>But this by the way, to ſhew what Gods Hand is.</p>
               <p>Now this Hand of God, is alſo the Hand of Chriſt the ſecond Perſon as made Fleſh; Its the Hand of Fleſh, eſpecially as riſen from the dead and glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the holy Ghoſt is his Breath, Shadow, Wings, Arme, Hands, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer proceedeth from him
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:1403:64"/> towards his Church, both Miniſters and people, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that eternall Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the third Perſon, who proceedeth from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Sonne, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.26. By which as <hi>High Prieſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>hee offered himſelfe without ſpot to God,</hi> as with his owne Hands; So now much more the ſame Spirit proceedth from him in more abundance from his Fleſh glorified. <hi>For before,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.39.</note> 
                  <hi>the Spirit was not giuen in that abundance, becauſe that Ieſus was not yet glorified.</hi> But now this Fleſh of Chriſt being glorified, this eternall Spirit is all the Breath, Armes, Hands, Strength, Shadow, Light, and Glory of Chriſt; He now breathes nothing but the holy Ghoſt and Spirit.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:1403:65"/> 
                  <hi>He breathed vpon his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſaid, Receiue ye the holy Ghoſt.</hi> He hath it now at command as his Breath, and as naturall to him, and can as eaſily and plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giue it; He holds the 7. Starres his Apoſtles, and Miniſters in his right hand, not of Fleſh, but of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and being riſen, he gaue commandements to his Apoſtles, not by a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane breath and voice, as before, but more ſpecially by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.2. See <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. <hi>The time ſhall come and now is, but ſhall be much more, that the dead ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of God, that is, ſhall</hi> ſhall haue his quickning ſpirit, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>The firſt Adam was made a liuing ſoule,</hi> and all that he could
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:1403:65"/> communicate to his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and children, if he had continued in innocency, had bin only a liuing ſoule, qualified with Gods holy Image: <hi>but the ſecond Adam is made a quickning ſpirit,</hi> which hee communicates to his members and poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and which proceedes from him. This Spirit is Chriſts light, by which he ſhines to vs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. <hi>Awake thou that ſleepest, and ſtand vp from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall ſhine vnto thee.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Whatſoeuer proceeds from Chriſts Fleſh now in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, is nothing but Spirit; <hi>He is aſcended farre aboue all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4.7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>to fill all things</hi> with his Spirit. Whereas there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is ſaid to feed vs from heauen with his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die as Manna, and to waſh
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:1403:66"/> vs from our ſinnes in his blood, to guide vs with his light, all this is nothing but his Spirit, which being pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by his death, comes as it were through his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood giuen to vs, as our own fleſh and blood. This Spirit is obtained and giuen by his death and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and comes to vs by his humane fleſh and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, into our fleſh and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.63.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore his Fleſh is called meate indeed, and his blood drinke indeede. For the fleſh of it ſelfe profiteth nothing,</hi> but becauſe for the merit of his ſufferings in his fleſh and by it, as by a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit the third Perſon the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, proceeding na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally from the Father and the Sonne, is hereby procured to flow, iſſue, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:1403:66"/> come forth to vs and into our hearts by grace. <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Becauſe yee are ſonnes</hi> reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne, <hi>God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Sonne into your hearts, which cryeth Abba Father.</hi> The Spirit doth and would euer naturally iſſue and proceed from God into vs, as <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17. did not our ſinnes ſtop the currant, and keepe him out of our hearts, by our indiſpoſition and vnworthineſſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capableneſſe of receiuing him, as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. <hi>Which the world cannot receiue, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him;</hi> but our ſins remooued and aboliſhed by the death &amp; ſacrifice of Chriſt, and by his fleſh and body broken, through it, as
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:1403:67"/> by a conduite the ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine hath its iſſue, and vent to flow into our ſinfull fleſh, and hearts, and God becomes againe that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>That liuing God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>that giues to all men ſimply without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, whatſoeuer his ſinnes he, and reproacheth no man,</hi> that by faith comes to him; <hi>but poures of his Spirit vpon all fleſh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.17.</note> This Spirit as its God the Fathers hand, ſo its Chriſts our Sauiours hand, the hand of fleſh, which Chriſt reacheth from heauen to vs, as to his brethren, and takes vs by the hand. Now that Chriſt is glorified in our fleſh and nature, that Spirit which from eternitie proceeded from the Father and the Sonne, and was as their breath and hand, by which
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:1403:67"/> they made the worlds, and breathed into mans face the breath of life, and made him a liuing ſoule; the ſame ſpirit and third perſon, doth now proceed from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt, as man, and from Chriſt the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon Incarnate, and is now both the breath of Chriſt, and the arme of Chriſt, which breath of eternall ſpirit, Chriſt now breathes into man dead in ſinne, to make him a new creature, created in Chriſt Ieſus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to good works, creating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new all the powers and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of ſoule and body, as it were new hands, and feete, quickned with a new life, for new motions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and ſeruices and workes; its the hand and arme of Chriſt, which
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:1403:68"/> he now reueales and makes bare from heauen, and thruſts into our hearts, quickning, and creating in vs new hands, that is, new faculties of our ſoules, to lay hold on and faſten on ſpirituall good, purchaſed by his death, and offered vs by his Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Chriſt by his Prieſtly Office, hath performed all things needfull for our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and prepared all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing matter. And by his Propheticall Office in the Miniſtery of his Word, of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fers vs himſelfe the ſecond Perſon incarnate to be our Sauiour, and all his ſauing benefits and ſpirit, if we will reach forth our hands, that is, the faculties of our ſoules, to receiue and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him; but our hands
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:1403:68"/> lye dead in ſinnes, that is, our minds and hearts from vnderſtanding, chooſing, willing and affecting any ſuch Perſon and his Spirit and benefits offered. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt as King riſen from the dead, and as Lord of life, reacheth forth his arme, &amp; hand from heauen, and creates in vs new hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is, new mindes and hearts; Hee breathes into vs the breath of life, that is, his quickning ſpirit, that quickens our dead hands, to apprehend ſpirituall things; <hi>For the naturall man, by his naturall ſoule and ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>as</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Spirit creates in vs. Firſt, a right hand of Faith, to know and apprehend the Perſon of the Son of God, and to chooſe, and take him
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:1403:69"/> for our Sauiour, as he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, and offered in the Word, reiecting all other Perſons, Angels, or Saints, or any creature, or our ſelues, and our workes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking our ſelues to Chriſt alone, and to this ſecond Perſon in Trinitie made fleſh, faſtning vpon him, and receiuing him as offered and commended to vs in the Goſpel, euen as crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and made our King, Prieſt, and Prophet, our Wiſedome, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſanctification, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and all that good which the Goſpel ſets him forth, and commends him vnto vs, <hi>Chriſt himſelfe giues vs ſuch a minde,</hi> 1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 5. <hi>The Sonne of God is come and hath giuen vs a minde to know him that is true,</hi> and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:1403:69"/> his infinite hand and arme, that is, his Spirit, creates this minde as a hand, by which we faſten vpon this Perſon, euen the hand of Faith, beleeuing the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, by which we are vnited to Chriſt this Perſon, and <hi>are in him that is true,</hi> and the only true Sauiour, <hi>that is, in his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, this is very God and eternall life,</hi> and therefore can by his Spirit, giue vs ſuch a minde to know him, and quicken our dead minds, as a liuing hand to apprehend his Perſon, with all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits offered to vs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Spirit and Hand of Chriſt creates and quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens in vs a left Hand, of a renewed Will and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For our wils and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections being dead in ſin,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:1403:70"/> ſelfe-loue, and luſts of the world, this Spirit breathes into them ſuch holy moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as caſts out theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked luſts, and ſwaies the will and affections to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, which ſpirit the Comforter ſo felt, quickning the will and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, they againe cloſe with this ſpirit, conſent to it, imbrace and hugge theſe holy motions, and reſigne vp themſelues with full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, to forſake all for his Spirit and Graces, and to be ruled, guided, and ſwayed only by this Spirit; as by the hand of Chriſt, and to be comforted, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and ordered by it. That as the Faith of the minde as a right hand, chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the right Perſon, and preferreth him before all,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:1403:70"/> and takes him only by the hand as a Mediatour, all-ſufficient to bring him to God; So the renued will and affections ioyne hands with his ſpirit, that om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent quickning hand which hath created them a new, and put a new life in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, by ſpirituall and diuine inſpiration; which Perſon with all his offices and benefits offered, and which hand of his ſpirit and ſpirituall motions and inſpirations felt in our hearts, by the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, when our hearts, wils, and affections, doe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> gladly imbrace, then Chriſt and wee are one, &amp; we goe hand in hand together to God, and to heauen, he lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs by the hand of his Spirit, and we following
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:1403:71"/> him by the motions, and inſpirations of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sonnes of God. But if any man haue not the Spirit of Chriſt, the ſame is none of his.</hi> Now ſome in hearing the Word, reſiſt, and put backe the hand of Chriſt, the holy Ghoſt, reiecting all ſpirituall motions, and will not bee led by them, but chooſing rather to follow their owne reaſon, fleſh, ſenſe, and luſts, to walke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh, not after the Spirit, as ſheepe that goe aſtray, and will not returne <hi>to Chriſt the Shepheard of their ſoules to bee led,</hi> and guided by him, 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.21. In preaching of the word, Chriſt ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorth his hands, that
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:1403:71"/> is, offereth vs his Spirit, to counſell, guide, inlighten, ſanctifie, and men refuſe it; which ſome doe ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Spirit hauing not inlightned their mindes, to inable them to diſcerne it ſelfe, to bee the hand of Chriſt graciouſly offered, and reached forth to them; and this is the common ſtate of the World, and of all ſinfull naturall men, as Chriſt ſheweth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. <hi>Which the world cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, becauſe it ſeeth him not, nor knoweth him,</hi> that is, which Spirit and hand of Chriſt, the world, and all naturall men cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, nor lay hands on, or ioyne hands with, becauſe they are not inlightned by it, to know it, &amp; Chriſt, and therefore cannot will, or
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:1403:72"/> deſire them, <hi>but yee know him, for hee dwelleth with you, and ſhall be</hi> in you.</p>
               <p>Some doe it vpon know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge wilfully, and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, who beeing made partakers of the holy ghoſt, and inlightened by it, ſo farre as to know Chriſtes perſon, the Lord of glory, and his Spirit of glory, and to ſee and diſcerne his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious arme, and power, and to taſte, and feele in ſome meaſure, and to perceiue the ſpirituall motions, and inſpirations of it, and the powers of the world to come, that is, the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vertues, and ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to a better life: but this Spirit, and the hand of God, not ouercomming the ſtony hardneſſe, and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitencie of the heart, and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:1403:72"/> will, dead as a ſtone in ſelfe loue, and luſts of the world, to make it reſolue to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it ſelfe, and its luſts, and the world, to receiue, and chooſe Chriſts perſon, benefits, counting all things as doung for him, and to imbrace the hand of his Spirit, and promiſes aboue all creatures, and his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall motions, and inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but though they know them to bee ſuch, yet for ſelfe-loue, and for their luſts ſake, to keepe them vnmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, they will rather fight againſt the ſpirit, checke it, and kill, and ſtrangle the good motions of the ſpirit, and rather crucifie Chriſt againe, and peirce through his hands and feete, then that hee ſhall crucifie their fleſh and luſts, and his hands
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:1403:73"/> mortifie them &amp; their luſts, and therefore through the rottenneſſe of their vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed hearts, they vtterly fall away from Chriſt his perſon, and Goſpel, whom they know, and haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and acknowledged, and maliciouſly hate him, and perſecute him, and his Miniſters, and members, and in the diſpoſition, and affection of their hearts, as much as in them lies, they crucifie againe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the Sonne of God, and make a mocke, and ſcorne of him, &amp; of ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and holineſſe, and tread vnder feete the Sonne of God, &amp; deſpight the ſpirit of grace, ſeeking to expoſe to all ſhame, godlineſſe, and ſinceritie, and godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and people, euen
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:1403:73"/> whom their conſciences know to be ſuch, and onely becauſe they profeſſe, and vrge the mortification of their fleſh, and luſts, and liuing, and walking ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, which their corrupt, and impenitent hearts, and willes cannot indure. <hi>But they that are Chriſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galat. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>haue crucified the fleſh, with the affections and luſts,</hi> that is in the heart, choice, will, and purpoſe, accepting, and allowing, and imbracing that, which Chriſt hath done for them to that end, which wicked men ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre and reiect, being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them.</p>
               <p>Some through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, reiect the gracious, &amp; mercifull hand of Chriſt, reached from Heauen, euen his Spirit, and ſauing ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:1403:74"/> and benefits. Some though knowing them by illumination of minde, and by ſome taſte of Diuine ſweetneſſe, and comfort in them: yet, ouercome of their luſts, and loue of the world, their hearts, and willes vnrenewed, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed, grow to hate, and deteſt them, ſeeking their deſtruction, and aboliſhing, becauſe they ſeeke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their fleſh, and luſts; and therefore had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt were againe crucified, and dead for euer in the graue, then that hee ſhould riſe, with ſuch hands of his Spirit, as ſhould cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie their fleſh, and luſts.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſuch is their malice, that they would euen pierce through theſe hands of Chriſts ſpirit, as
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:1403:74"/> the Iewes pierced through, and crucified through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, fleſhly Chriſt, as I may ſay, in the dayes of his fleſh, when he was in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſement, to whom Chriſt promiſeth pardon vpon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;<note place="margin">Matth. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man ſpeake a word, againſt the Sonne of man,</hi> that is, as onely know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him as a Man, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of his God-head, and Spirit, it may bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen him: <hi>But if any man blaſpheame the Holy ghost, and God-head of Chriſt ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> and ſparkling in him, it <hi>ſhall neuer bee forgiuen him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some now maliciouſly, crucifie Spirituall Chriſt, riſen from the dead, and ſhining into their hearts, and ſoules, by his Spirit, and comming to apply his
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:1403:75"/> Croſſe, and Death, to cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie their fleſh, and luſts, by his Spirit, and Spirituall hands: they now, not as in the dayes of his fleſh, but in the eternitie of his Spirit, and Glory, would crucifie againe, and aboliſh for euer.</p>
               <p>They that are thus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected towards the ſpirit, are ſaid to be ſo affected to Chriſt; becauſe the Spirit is Chriſts hand, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it reueales, preſents, and offers Chriſts perſon, merits, righteouſneſſe, and the ſauing vertue of his Croſſe, to crucifie all our luſts, <hi>for this ſpirit takes of Christ, and ſhewes it vnto vs, Ioh.</hi> 16.9, 10. it comes with its hands full of Chriſt. So that as I loue Chriſt, and take him by the hand, when
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:1403:75"/> I gladly imbrace his Spirit, and ſuffer my ſelfe to bee led by it, and its ſpirituall motions: ſo contrarily, they hate Chriſt, and crucifie him, and pierce through his hands, that hate his Spirit, and deſtroy his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall motions ſuggeſted to their hearts.</p>
               <p>For as ſome of the Iewes, through ignorance of Chriſts God-head, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Chriſt onely, as a poore man, the Carpenters ſonne, that had proudly vſurped a Kingdome ouer them, and againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and therefore put him to death as a Traitor, and as onely crucifying his fleſhly hands: Yet ſome others, and eſpecially the Scribes and Phariſees that knew him by the light of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:1403:76"/> the Holy Ghoſt, that hee was God, and by the finger of God had caſt out deuils, (as Chriſt knowing their hearts, profeſſeth they did) They crucified him not as the Sonne of man, nor one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his fleſhly hands, as hee was the Carpenters ſonne, but his Spirituall hands, as he was the Sonne of God, hating his ſpirit and power, in the Miniſtery of his Word, and Miracles, and Doctrine, and Diſciples, for which ſake they chiefely crucified him, that if they could poſſibly, they might aboliſh for euer his Name, Doctrine, Religion, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Spirit, and Church, which now began to bee gathered. Hee was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of theſe, not as the Sonne of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> but as the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:1403:76"/> Anointed, and Holy One of God, anointed with the Holy Ghoſt, and with power, doing what they could to crucifie the Holy ghoſt, &amp; to pierce through the hands and feete of the Spirit. They trode vnder feet, not the ſonne of man, but the Sonne of God, and made a mocke of him. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in confidence, Chriſt leading, and taking vs by the hand, and we lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold on his fleſh cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for vs, wee goe confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently. If wee lay hold on any creature elſe, and bee led &amp; guided by any Saint, or Angel, wee goe with feare, and doubting, with perplexitie, and anxietie, when conſcience of ſinne accuſeth vs, and are neuer
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:1403:77"/> ſecure, that wee ſhall bee ſaued. To bee bould and confident with God at any time, but eſpecially in the conſcience of ſinne, is a marueilous courage: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſe face and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the Angels are aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, the mountaines melt, whoſe Maieſtie and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is, ſo glorious, feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and terrible, that no creature can abide his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, when hee is angry. The moſt Holy Angels without ſpot of ſinne in nature, and conſcience, yet couer their faces, as aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at his preſence, though doing his will, in obeying the voyce of his mouth.</p>
               <p>How much more muſt ſinfull man, duſt and aſhes melt, and bee confounded with ſhame, and horrour,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:1403:77"/> at the preſence of ſo Holy a God? yet Faith in Chriſt, makes confident and bold. <hi>Iacob</hi> had ſtrength, and courage, &amp; preuailed with God. <hi>Moſes</hi> indured as ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, that is inuiſible, by this Faith in Chriſt, who at Horeb in the giuing of the Law, where the ſight was ſo terrible, hee confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I feare and quake. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Wee not onely glory in afflictions,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> which ſome ſtout hearted carnall men haue done by pride, ambition, or ſtrength of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who vpon the ſight of God, haue trembled like <hi>Belteſhar, but wee alſo glory in God,</hi> ſee 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17. &amp; 3.21. <hi>Abrahams</hi> boldneſſe was with God, to parle with him, though hee was but duſt and aſhes.</p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:1403:78"/>
               <p>Wee ſee how hard a thing it is, to be bold in the preſence of a King, a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man, eſpecially if he be angry: His wrath is like the roaring of a Lyon: How much more to bee bold in the preſence of God, the King of Kings, when hee is angry, <hi>who cutteth off the ſpirit of Princes, who is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to the Kings of the earth, that they feare in their Priuie-chambers? Pſa.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.5.</p>
               <p>Sinne weakens, and breakes the heart, and ſoule of man, by breeding doubts, feares, griefes, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings, and horrours: So the Deuils, and <hi>Adam,</hi> by their fall, brake themſelues into ſhiuers of feares, and tremblings. And as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill trembles, ſo our corrupt
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:1403:78"/> nature, and guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, like his, is to doe as the Deuill doeth; for wee are broken, and infected like him by ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>when wee were yet of no ſtrength, Christ died for vs,</hi> that is, when wee were broken, and infected with the guilt of all ſinnes. Therefore the Lawe, firſt breakes vs, and kils vs with the ſight, and guilt of ſinne, before Chriſt cures vs, and binds vs vp; and this is the cure of the heart, and ſoule, by Faith in Chriſts blood, and breaking for vs, his ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, horrours, griefes, and paines, in ſoule and body, that <hi>we are ſtrengthened with confidence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>by his ſpirit in the inner-man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.7</note> and <hi>haue not the ſpirit of feare, but of power and loue, and of a ſound
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:1403:79"/> minde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.15 Iſa. 61.1.</note> 
                  <hi>not the ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, to feare againe, but of adoption, to cry</hi> confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Abba Father: This is to bind vp the broken hearted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore is Chriſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Rocke of the ſoule, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Vpon this Rocke will I build my Church,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee giues the heart, and ſoule, built on it by Faith, ſtrength of courage, nd confidence. <hi>Therefore the fearefull, and vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, are caſt out with dogs. Reuel.</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is the Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the ſoule chiefely, and therefore from feares, doubts, and griefes chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and from the ſpirit of bondage, to feare againe. The chiefeſt vertue of bread, is to incourage, and ſtrengthen the heart: So
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:1403:79"/> Chriſt crucified, his body broken, and fed on by faith, its vertue is, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, and ſtrengthen the heart with confidence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</p>
               <p>If therefore wee feele feare, fainting, doubting, goe the more to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſtes body, which as it requires ſome courage, and hope, that we ſhall finde ſtrength, and nouriſhment of confidence by it; ſo it alſo giues it, and makes vs bold with God, and feareleſſe of ſinne, and death, as Chriſt incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. vlt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Therefore renouncing all other meanes of courage, and confidence, and ſeeking not to make our ſelues ſafe, and bould in our ſelues, our workes, righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:1403:80"/> wealth, friends, let vs goe onely by Faith to Chriſt, to giue all true confidence, ſecuritie, and comfort of minde, and heart, by his death, and blood, as the onely bread of life, and ſtrength to the ſoule, and of cordiall vertues.</p>
               <p>For all carnall men feele feare, and griefe, and anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of minde, and in this ſenſe, they go to the world, and wealth, to the Lawe, and workes, and ſeeke to ſecure, and ſtrengthen, and free themſelues from theſe feares, and griefes, and to heale themſelues by wealth, and truſting here to, and ſay, If I could doe, and liue, thus, and thus, and had ſo much wealth, or performe this, or that righteouſneſſe: then my
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:1403:80"/> minde would be quiet, and at reſt, and feareleſſe. But theſe things can neuer giue ſecuritie, and reſt to the minde, and heart, but vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. Goe to Chriſt by Faith, and hee will giue thee reſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. verſe the laſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Therefore confidence is as well a fruit of Faith, as the forme of Faith. For Faith goes to Chriſt, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of it ſelfe, its life, and ſtrength of confidence. It could not goe at all to Chriſt, if it had not ſome ſtrength, and life of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: but becauſe it feeles weakeneſſe, of feare, and doubting, it goes to Chriſt to bee incouraged, and ſtrengthened, and quickned more, <hi>crying,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 17.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord increaſe our faith,</hi> and giue vs mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:1403:81"/> courage, and ſtrength of Faith in heart, by feeding vs with thy body, and blood,<note place="margin">Mar. 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord I beleeue, helpe my vnbeleefe.</hi> Therefore he ſaith here, by Faith of him, that is, by going to Chriſt by Faith, and betaking our ſelues to him, and laying hold on him, wee haue a confident acceſſe to God, with more confidence, then we can haue by laying hold on, and chooſing any other to lead vs. Therefore eate his Body, and drinke his Blood, that is, take and chooſe his Death, &amp; blood, for your onely meate, to nouriſh, &amp; ſtrengthen your hearts with comfort, and peace, as onely cordiall, to giue you courage, and confidence againſt ſinne, &amp; Satan, and boldneſſe with
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:1403:81"/> God, and it will doe ſo. For as meate requires ſome life, and ſtrength, to take, eate, and digeſt it, and ſo it giues, and increaſeth more life, and ſtrength to the heart: So Chriſt the bread of life, requires ſome ſtrength of Faith, to receiue him, and digeſt him, and ſo he giues more ſtrength, and courage with God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne.</p>
               <p>Therefore we muſt goe to the Sacrament, as well to increaſe faith, as to bring Faith with vs. In going, we muſt by Faith renounce all comfort, and confidence in our ſelues, and all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and goe out of them to Chriſt onely, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him, that hee may giue vs all true boldneſſe, and confidence towardes
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:1403:82"/> God, that nothing may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs, but Chriſt, and that hee may giue vs better courage, then any other creature can giue vs.</p>
               <p>Chooſe, and take Chriſt, for thy onely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy guide, and Captaine to lead thee to God, and hee will incourage thee, with inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible ſtrength, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and giue thee a heart of ſteele: but truſt to any thing elſe, and it will faile thy heart, and not be a ſure Rocke to it, but leaue it in feare, doubting, anxietie. Goe to Chriſt onely, and hee will giue the legges to goe better, and ſtrengthen thy feeble knees, and make ſtraight ſteps to thy feete, and incourage thy heart to come more to him, and to God by him: but goe to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:1403:82"/> any other, and they will increaſe thy feares, doubts, and ſcruples. Take heart to goe to God by Chriſt, &amp; incourage thy heart, and hee will giue thee more courage; <hi>Bee ſtrong, and he ſhall ſtrengthen your hearts. Pſal.</hi> 26.14.</p>
               <p>All true Miniſters and Chriſtians boldneſſe, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to preach, or goe to Gods houſe, to appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, to worſhip him, is by faith in Chriſt, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, as ſeeing him, and in ſinceritie approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the heart to him, as beholding him in Chriſt, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.1, 2. The hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites boldneſſe is only to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men, in blindneſſe and darkneſſe, not ſeeing God, but only men, whoſe eyes and eares they can
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:1403:83"/> pleaſe, and only ſatisfie their exſpectation. If Miniſters could manifeſt Gods face and preſence, and God would ſhew himſelfe in them, as in the Primitiue Church; only beleeuers durſt ioyne themſelues to the Church, and to the Lord: hypocrites would ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abhorre, or tremble, or bee aſhamed to appeare, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.13, 14. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24, 25.</p>
               <p>The beſt and greateſt boldneſſe and confidence is towards God. Diuels and wicked men by ſinne, pride, malice, or by wealth, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, authoritie, power, may be bold towards ſin full men, weake and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and baſe like the earth as themſelues: but they haue no courage or bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:1403:83"/> towards God, but quake and tremble at his Maieſtie; and eſpecially when they are ouermat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by death, or any other euill. They that are bold in mans day, only beholding man, ſhall tremble in the Lords day, when God ſhall exalt himſelfe. Such as put their ſtrength and confidence in their wealth, pride, malice, are moſt feareful and cowardly with God and death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let vs draw neere with a true heart in aſſurance of Faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.22</note> without all doubt and ſcruple, <hi>ſeeing we haue ſuch an all ſufficient High Priest ouer the Houſe of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 7.25</note> that <hi>can perfectly ſaue them that come to God by him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 7.26</note> 
                  <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, harmeleſſe, vndefiled, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from ſinners, and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:1403:84"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:1403:84"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:1403:85"/> higher then the heauens,</hi> that hath all-ſufficiencie, of all-ſauing good, as King, Prieſt, and Prophet, to vanquiſh, and remooue all ſinnes, and deuils, and to conferre all good.</p>
               <p>Receiue Chriſt into thee by faith, lay hold on him to lead thee, renouncing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp; ſenſe, that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be ſtrong, and confident without all feare. For therefore we feare, and are in doubt, becauſe we looke to our ſelues, and to our owne ſtrength, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and reſt thereon, and goe not wholly out of our ſelues to Chriſt, to reſt our hearts on him, and to receiue him onely into vs, to comfort, and incourage vs, but wee receiue the World, or our workes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:1403:85"/> our hearts, and feede on them, which will neuer ſtrengthen our hearts. This bread wants that ſtaffe, and ſtrength, and vertue to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our hearts againſt ſinne, Satan, and ſo many croſſes, that they cannot be ſtrong, but full of feare and doubting, becauſe they are not built on Chriſt the Rocke, and are not fedde with his body broken, and blood ſhed, which only is that bread which ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the heart of man to goe to God, without feare and fainting. For there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was Chriſts ſoule and heart, and body broken with feare, fainting, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, that ours might bee bound vp and healed.</p>
               <p>If we haue no boldneſſe with men, but feare their
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:1403:86"/> earthen faces, &amp; tremble at their wrath, whoſe breath is in their noſtrils: If the conſcience of ſinne make vs tremble before men: how much more before God the Iudge? 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.12, 13. Seeke bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with God. Its no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing what boldneſſe we haue with men, that our hearts and conſciences warrant vs to ſtand vpon Interrogatories with men, and challenge, Who dare lay any thing to our charg? and we can ſhew our faces in any court, &amp; ſtand vpon our righteouſneſſe But dare we doe ſo with God, and ſtand vpon interrogatories with him, either in Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, as 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. or San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification,<note place="margin">Pſal. 138.23.</note> as <hi>Dauid,</hi> Lord <hi>Prooue mee and try mee if
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:1403:86"/> there be any way of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in me?</hi> In whom wee haue acceſſe with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as we haue our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to God out of our ſelues only in &amp; by Chriſt, ſo we haue our confidence only in Chriſt, and not in our ſelues.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in regard of the matter, all matter of confi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dence is only in Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> his Death, Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Merits, Righteouſneſſe, Interceſſion, as 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 21. and 3.21, 22. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.9. with <hi>verſe</hi> 8. and 13, 14. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.9.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as the Rocke and efficient cauſe of our actuall confidence, diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to vs arbitrarily, as he ſees fit, and we need, as enemies, troubles and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers increaſe. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:1403:87"/> in vs naturally but feare, and a ſpirit of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and weaknes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are bound, and goe faintly, but Chriſt ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth and breatheth into vs a ſpirit of courage, and confidence aboue that we haue by faith, whereof faith is an inſtrument and meanes to draw it forth. Our hearts naturally medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate feare, and we weaken and diſcourage our ſelues, and Chriſt incourageth vs, and giues vs ſtrength and confidence. We muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that there is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confidence. 1. Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, which is in faith, a kinde of naturall child-like confidence ſeeded in vs, whereby we are well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of Gods fatherly heart and good will, as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:1403:87"/> children naturally are of their parents affection, and yet vpon all dangers and miſcarriages, or other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, they feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble through weakeneſſe of iudgement, and apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and imbecillitie of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in which infirmities its the parents wiſedome and indulgency to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and comfort,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.4.</note> not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to be furiouſly angry leaſt they be diſcouraged</hi> and all together put out of heart. So is it with God and his children; they haue ſome child-like perſwaſion of God the Father his Loue, by which they goe to him; which perſwaſion is ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in their hearts, the firſt habite of Faith, but which is not of ſtrength to carry them to God with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:1403:88"/> when conſcience of ſinnes, Satan and Enemies, and dangers aſſault, but by weakeneſſe of iudgement and apprehenſion, and frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the fleſh, they are ready deſperatly to cry out for feare, as the Diſciples did at the ſight of Chriſt comming like a ghoſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the waters, till Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them, &amp; ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them ſaying; It is I, be not afraid, Chriſt is not fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly angry againſt our infirmities, feares, doubts, <hi>but ſpareth vs as a Father ſpareth his childe that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him</hi> as well as he can,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> though with neuer ſuch weakeneſſe and frailtie; and he ſupports vs in our feares and doubts, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 93.18. <hi>When I ſaid my foote ſlippeth thy mercy O Lord held mee
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:1403:88"/> vp.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 93.19.</note> 
                  <hi>In the multitude of the thoughts of my heart,</hi> that is full of feares, doubtings, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, <hi>thy comforts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce my ſoule.</hi> So Chriſt giues all beleeuers confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, diſpenſing it, as we need againſt our many ſins, temptatious, dangers, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. For as our life is hid with Chriſt in God, ſo is our confidence, which is our life and ſtrength, increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and diſpenſed as Chriſt pleaſeth, as 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 20.20. <hi>Trust in the Lord, and yee ſhall be aſſured,</hi> that is, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident. If yee by faith goe only to God, beleeuing that he is able and willing, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe to helpe, and chooſe him only for your Sauiour, and protector, and reiecting all other, betake your ſelues to
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:1403:89"/> him alone, he will not only ſaue you, but giue aſſurance and ſecuritie of ſaluation before-hand, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the greateſt part of ſaluation, the healing of the ſoule of ſinfull feares, doubts, and ſcruples, and ſtabliſhing the heart and minde in peace paſſing all vnderſtanding, as I haue before touched.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiect.</hi> I feare my faith is not true, becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be confidently aſſured that God will helpe me, not reſt therein without feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our Faith may be true though weake, and ioyned with feare. Let vs ſtriue therefore againſt the feare and weakneſſe of our nature, and fleſh, and vſe our weake faith to go vnto
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:1403:89"/> Chriſt, and he will giue vs ſtrong confidence. That is his gift, and not of our ſelues. Its that fruit, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther growth and increaſe of the firſt faith, ſowen in our hearts rightly improo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.14. <hi>Be ſtrong and he ſhall ſtrengthen your hearts, and truſt in the Lord,</hi> that is, doe you improoue your weake faith to goe to Chriſt, ſeeking to him for ſtrength and courage, and increaſe of your faith, and goe not to any creatures, to make your ſelues ſtrong, confident, and ſecure in them, and Chriſt will giue you confidence and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.26. <hi>My fleſh faileth me, and my heart al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, but God is the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:1403:90"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This makes greatly for the comfort of the weake in faith. And let vs not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect a faith without feare, infirmitie, anxietie: but ſtriue againſt this weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and lament it, and vſe this weake faith in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt, to ſtrengthen it with confidence. The chiefe treaſure of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and of this life of faith, Chriſt keepes in his owne hand, and will haue vs in the ſenſe of our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of faith in his promiſe to goe to him for it, and depend on him to keepe, ſtrengthen and ſupport our weake faith, as he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,<note place="margin">Matth. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>That hee will not quench the ſmoaking flaxe, nor breake the bruiſed reede.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We haue a ſmall roote of faith in our ſelues, but
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:1403:90"/> the body and truncke is in Chriſt: by this ſmall roote we liue and goe to Chriſt, and cleaue to him, and ſigh to him in our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and being thus hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, we depend on him daily to ſupport our faith, &amp; increaſe our confidence, which we muſt not looke to haue alwaies in our ſelues, but in and from Chriſt as his free grace ſhall arbitrarily diſpenſe the ſame.</p>
               <p>Therfore he ſuffers ſome of his Saints, and members to be more weake then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and fearefull, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome he infuſeth a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpirit of confidence. Some goe weakely and faintly all their daies, and <hi>can hardly lift vp their weake hands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>and feeble
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:1403:91"/> knees, to make ſtreight ſteps to their feete.</hi> And this Chriſt doth partly for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his owne grace, and mercy in ſupporting ſuch weake ones, and for exerciſe of our mercy and loue. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1, 2. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.7. As the ſoule infuſeth not the like vigour, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of life, comfort, ſtrength into all the members of the body: So nor Chriſt.</p>
               <p>We muſt as well goe to Chriſt for faith and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as for any other grace, and he requires of vs perſwaſion and faith, that wee ſhall receiue it from him, <hi>viz.</hi> that he will in dangers, feares, ſinnes, temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, ſtrengthen, incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and comfort vs againſt them all, euen death, and hell, and all enemies. Say
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:1403:91"/> not, I am a creature ſo weak and faint in faith, that I ſhall neuer ſtand againſt theſe. Caſt not away thy weake faith, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.35. Sit not ſtill, and keepe not thy bed, becauſe thou canſt not goe ſo ſtrongly to Chriſt as others can; but goe as well as thou canſt with thy <hi>feeble weake knees,</hi> and <hi>let not that which is hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting be turned out of the way but rather be healed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> Seeke for more ſtrength of faith, rather then deſpaire and caſt away all faith. Fight the good fight of faith, and ſtriue to lay hold on Chriſt and he will ſtrengthen thy faith; only ſeeke not to ſtrengthen and ſecure thy heart in wealth, pollicie, thy owne righteouſneſſe. For he is the ſheepheard of
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:1403:92"/> our ſoules,<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> and hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to conuert our ſoules and to dwell in our hearts, if we by faith chooſe him to dwell in vs, to bee his houſe, reiecting all other lords and ſpirits, then will he come into vs and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs by his Spirit in the inner man, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.16, 17. and he dwelling in vs, as <hi>in his houſe, we ſhall hold fast our confidence and hope of reioycing vnto the End. Heb.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Therefore pray as the <hi>Diſciples,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 17.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord increaſe our Faith,</hi> and cry <hi>as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Daemoniake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord I beleeue, helpe my vnbeleefe,</hi> and giue me confidence; and beleeue that hee will pardon thy weake faith, and heale it, as well as any other thy ſinnes and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:1403:92"/> as long as they are but infirmities which thou ſtriueſt againſt, lamenteſt and laboureſt for ſtrength of faith, deſiring aboue all to honour God with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Beleeue hee will pardon the want of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, as long as thou ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt and laboureſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and doeſt not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect infidelitie <hi>with an euill heart of infidelitie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3.</note> totally euill and vnfaithfull, <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part away from the liuing God,</hi> and to forſake him our Rocke and portion, chooſing and preferring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>vlt.</hi> For that which our hearts chooſe for our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they truſt in, and are ſtrong and confident in. <hi>Where our treaſure is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math 6.</note> 
                  <hi>there will our hearts bee alſo.</hi>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:1403:93"/> Lam. 3. <hi>The Lord is my Portion, ſaith my ſoule, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I trust in him.</hi> Hereby I know, I haue ſome true faith, though with much feare, when I chooſe God to bee my chiefe portion, to be ſecure, confident and feareleſſe in him. As a ſeruant that chooſeth a Maſter, in whoſe power, riches, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, for protection and maintenance, he repoſeth himſelfe to quiet, ſecure and reſt his heart in him. Some chooſe wealth; ſome the Arme of fleſh; But a Chriſtian by faith choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Chriſt. Therefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>A man cannot ſerue two Maſters, to repoſe confidence and ſafety in them both, but wee muſt either cleaue to the one, and deſpiſe
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:1403:93"/> the other, or hate the one, and loue the other. So yee cannot ſerue God and Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> to ſeeke ſafetie and ſecuritie from them both. The heart ſeekes its ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty but in one treaſure. See <hi>Math.</hi> 6.21.24. That which is our portion giues vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence; It belongs not to our Faith, but to our porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which faith chooſeth, and pitcheth on, to giue vs confidence. Chooſe God for thy portion, to reſt thy heart in him, as he hath promiſed to be the Rocke of thy heart, and then try and ſee, if God doe not giue thy heart ſecure confidence as a Rocke, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.26. and 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.20. Truſt in the Lord and ye ſhall be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured. Let thy heart bee Chriſts houſe to dwell in
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:1403:94"/> thee by faith, &amp; thou ſhalt ſee, that he will ſtrengthen thee by his Spirit in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner man, not to faint or feare in any afflictions, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.13, 16. Thou ſhalt then ſenſibly feele &amp; know, that Chriſt is in thee, and thou art his houſe, in that thy <hi>heart keepes this confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and hope of reioycing vnto the End,</hi> as <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. that is, hereby we ſenſibly know it. We are Chriſts houſe before by faith; but we doe not ſo ſenſibly feele and know it, that he dwels in vs, till he as the Maſter of the houſe, ſtrengthen and incourage our hearts.</p>
               <p>Wicked men and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers doe not beleeue, that Chriſt can or will ſtrengthen their hearts, to make them ſtrong and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:1403:94"/> without feare and griefe, therefore they put their ſtrength and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in wealth, pride, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pride is to them as a chaine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 7.3.</note> 
                  <hi>cruelty couers them as a garment.</hi> They arme themſelues with theſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of the fleſh, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden &amp; incourage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by them, and not in God and Chriſt their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They ſeeke freedome from care, feare, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of minde in wealth and honour, and promiſe to themſelues all ſecuritie of minde and heart, and ſafety of life, and eſtate in theſe things, as <hi>Luke</hi> 12. <hi>My ſoule take thine eaſe, eate and drinke, thou hast much goods laide vp for many yeares.</hi> Contrary, a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:1403:95"/> heart, beleeues as God ſaith, not as Satan, Reaſon and fleſh ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> that though he had <hi>all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>yet his life ſtands not in his riches,</hi> and though hee had all the world, it will not keepe his minde and heart ſafe from feares, cares, griefe, nor his body and life ſafe, quiet, nor ſecure, but only God and Chriſts loue and mercy, and therefore nothing will content him but theſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore hee goeth to God, and Chriſt, onely to repoſe his ſoule in them, and hauing them, he is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded as the word ſaith, that his ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe, and bee ſecure, <hi>his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſhall bee the munition of rockes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Name of the Lord will be a ſtrong Tower</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 18.</note>
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:1403:95"/> 
                  <hi>to him,</hi> if he could attaine to it, that he ſhould lie downe in peace, and ſleepe, <hi>and riſe againe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe the Lord would make him dwell in ſafetie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>that bread ſhould</hi> be giuen him, and his waters ſhould bee ſure: But the wilfull infidelitie of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers, makes them reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly to conclude, and ſay, <hi>Who is the Almighty, that they ſhould ſerue him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 21.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and what profit ſhould they haue, that they ſhould pray vnto him?</hi> They count not God any ſuch ſecure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge,<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and therefore make falſehood their refuge, and vnder vanitie hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They cannot reſt nor ſleepe, without their God Mammon, their chiefe por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their bellies filled
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:1403:96"/> with that meate that peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth. Contrary, a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian cannot reſt, nor ſleepe, feeling his ſoule emptie of God, and Chriſt, and the meat that indureth to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. Becauſe hee beleeues, that Chriſts body broken, is that onely bread of life, that can quicken, and ſtrengthen his heart, with courage, comfort, and confidence inuincible, and therefore chooſeth no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foode but this, <hi>and layes foorth his money,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and labour chiefely for this, Iohn</hi> 6.27. being perſwaded that all nouriſhing, comforting, and ſtrengthning vertue to the heart, is in Chriſtes death, blood, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and that all other bread <hi>is but aſhes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 44.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and that a ſeduced heart deceiueth
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:1403:96"/> men, that they cannot deliuer their ſoules</hi> from feeding on theſe vanities.</p>
               <p>If wee beleeue, that all comfort, and confidence is in Chriſt crucified, and goe to him for it, we ſhall find him indeed, that bread of life, that will giue life, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ſtrength, courage, as he promiſeth, by his word, and Sacraments. In which Faith, and ſenſe of his feares deadneſſe, <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo often repaires to God, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Quicken mee, O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> 
                  <hi>according to thy promiſe.</hi> Let vs likewiſe, goe to Chriſt, and ſay; Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, thou haſt promiſed, that if wee come to thee, thou wilt giue vs life, if wearied with our pride, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie, feares, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, wee lament the ſame,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:1403:97"/> and come to thee, thou wilt eaſe, and refreſh vs, with ſtrength in our ſoules, and not breake the bruiſed reed.</p>
               <p>Lord Ieſus, renouncing all other meanes of eaſing, reſting, and refreſhing my ſoule, and heart, and of giuing mee comfort, and confidence, and to free me from my feares, and cares, &amp; ſinfull troubles of minde, I come onely to thee, the Shepheard of my ſoule,<note place="margin">See Hoſ. 14.3.</note> who calleſt mee vnto thee, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. and <hi>Pſal. When I am afraid, I will truſt in thee.</hi> Therefore Lord eaſe, and refreſh my minde, with confident reſt, and repoſe in thee, from all feare, doubting, anxietie. Thou haſt promiſed to giue to the thirſtie ſoule, that
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:1403:97"/> faints with feare, griefe, and trouble of minde like the parched ground that gapes, the water of life.</p>
               <p>Lord Ieſus, thou waſt weary, and thirſtie in body, and ſoule, &amp; askedſt drinke, both Spirituall,<note place="margin">See Heb. 4 15. &amp; 2.17, 18.</note> and bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereby thou perfitly knoweſt, what it is to haue a wearie, faint, and thirſtie ſoule, full of feare, griefe, doubting, and didſt promiſe the water of life, which I beleeue, thou onely haſt to giue, and wilt giue, and therefore I come to thee. I know, and beleeue, that thou promiſeſt no more, then thou canſt performe, and that thy Spirit, and righteouſneſſe can doe it, and therefore I renounce all other meanes of refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and come to thee, as
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:1403:98"/> thou calleſt mee, <hi>crying, in the last,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 7.37.</note> 
                  <hi>and great day of the Feast,</hi> promiſing to make a better Feaſt then that was, or all the Feaſtes of the yeere, euen a continuall Feaſt, to all that are thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and come to thee, to drinke, to refreſh, and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their hearts deſires, in thee onely, as our Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer ſacrificed for vs. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7, 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> But my feares, and griefes, and deſpaires, are ſo great, that I feele no faith at all, but all faith, and hope is ſwallowed vp.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> It is ſo to ſenſe, but not ſo indeed, as with <hi>Ieremie, Lament.</hi> 3. <hi>My ſtrength, and my hope is periſhed from the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, its not a wilfull, willing, and obſtinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:1403:98"/> reiecting all counſell, and meanes of confidence, as in <hi>Ahaz. Iſa.</hi> 7.12. but a deſperation, lamented, and ſtriuen againſt, with ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to any counſell, and meanes for the cure, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and prizing Faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not damnable.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, eſpecially if thou canſt thus doe, which is my counſell to thee, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to doe, that is, to goe to Chriſt, though quaking, and trembling, and full of feare: flie not from Chriſt, to any creature for refuge and confidence,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.20.</note> 
                  <hi>for that is to goe after vaine things, that cannot profit.</hi> Though by feares, and doubts wee ſinne, and offend Chriſt, yet, flie not from Chriſt, the only medicine of ſinne,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:1403:99"/> &amp; cure of doubts, &amp; infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, eſpecially, he calling, &amp; commanding thee to come vnto him. Therefore obey his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, &amp; hope aboue hope, and beleeue aboue thy faith, that his grace &amp; mercy, wil pardon, and heale thy infidelitie, &amp; ſay, I will not vtterly feare, &amp; deſpaire, but in deſpight of my feares, &amp; diſtruſtfull heart, and Satans temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I will goe to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he commands me; If I cannot goe by faith, yet, I will goe by obedience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he commands mee to come to him, and not ſuffer my feares to keepe mee backe: I will reſolutely caſt my ſelfe on him; if I cannot doe it faithfully, yet, with a wilfull reſolution to obey, his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement: though
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:1403:99"/> I cannot doe it with heart and affection, &amp; delight, as I would, and ſhould doe it. Euen deſpairing of all hope from him of any good, yet wilfully, and reſolutely, caſt thy ſelfe on him, ſaying, if hee will let mee periſh, ſo let it bee, I will goe to him, though without all hope, and commend my ſelfe to him, and if I periſh, I periſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> Oh, but I can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> Yet, goe and caſt thy feare, and infidelitie, and all thy ſinnes on him, who hath ſatisfied for them all, and muſt heale them all; chiding thy ſelfe for thy feares, and doubts, <hi>Why art thou ſo caſt downe my ſoule,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>and diſquieted within me? waite on God, &amp; Chriſt,</hi> and in deſpight of deſpaire,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:1403:100"/> with a contrary deſperate reſolution, aboue all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſenſe, or hope, ſay as <hi>Ionas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ionas 2.</note> 
                  <hi>yet will I looke towardes thy holy Temple,</hi> though to all reaſon, and ſenſe, I am <hi>vtterly cast out from thy preſence for euer,</hi> I will not yet giue ouer prayer, I will yet fight the good fight of Faith, I will caſt my ſelfe on him.</p>
               <p>As there is in ſome wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, a deſperate wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of ruſhing into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, againſt all meanes of reſtraint both of promiſes, threats, mercies, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings from God, and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, &amp; prouocations from men, and a deſperate will in men, to aduenture vpon deſperate meanes, as if they were mad, vpon no ground of reaſon or hope, but only
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:1403:100"/> their owne fooliſh creduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, beleeuing their owne conceit, and following the hardneſſe of their owne hearts and deſperate wils, ſo much will they attribute and ſacrifice ſuch honour to the Godhead of their conceit and will: That ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour doe thou giue to Chriſt, by a deſperate reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of a holy will, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to God, aboue all hope, and againſt all feares of apparent euils and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, to all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, vpon a credence of Gods word and promiſe, againſt all arguments of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, caſt thy ſelfe vpon Chriſt, becauſe hee bids thee. As <hi>Peter</hi> at Chriſts commandement goes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the waters, and at his commandement caſts forth
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:1403:101"/> his net, to make a draught againſt all doubts and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of deſpaire. Such authority giues Faith to Chriſts commaundement, and word, and ſuch is the obedience of Faith.</p>
               <p>Obey not therefore thy owne feares, and doubts, to beleeue &amp; follow them, but obey Chriſts commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to beleeue againſt all reaſon, and ſenſe, feares, doubts, and deſpaires. This is the obedience of Faith, ſimple, and abſolute, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reaſon why, but onely becauſe Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. For its Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer our ſinnes, and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, our feares, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and infidelitie be, and how great ſo euer our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery be; that yet we ſhould
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:1403:101"/> beleeue, that hee will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and heale all. Nay, becauſe our miſery by ſins, and puniſhments of God, on ſoule and body, are great, and deſperate, paſſing all created power, to cure, or helpe them; therefore to beleeue, and to goe to him, ordained of God, a Phyſitian, to heale all that are deſperately ſicke, and diſeaſed, and paſt all hope, in reaſon and ſenſe: Yet, there is hope in Chriſt, and hee commaunds vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, and vpon his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, to goe to him, to eaſe vs of the burden of our ſinnes, and miſeries, when they lie ſo heauy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, and ſo faſtned on vs, as we conceiue no poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of remoouing them, nor of any eaſe, and refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:1403:102"/> from any creature, promiſing, that he will giue vs reſt.</p>
               <p>Obey the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which commaunds thee to beleeue, againſt all vnbeleefe, and aboue all beleefe, and to hope, aboue hope, that is, in infinite doubtings, to beleeue, and in all deſpaires, to hope, and when all reaſons, grounds, meanes, and hopes are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, yet to beleeue, only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God commands thee ſo to doe. Though nature, reaſon, ſenſe, and thy owne heart, &amp; faithleſſe feares, &amp; all creatures forbid thee ſo to doe,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.</note> ſaying, <hi>That thy ſtrength, and hope, is peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from the Lord,</hi> yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, and beleeue none of theſe, but Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, commanding thee
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:1403:102"/> to beleeue his promiſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them all, and ſo to honour him as God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue them all in power, mercy, trueth, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
               <p>Though they ſay, thy caſe is deſperate, God ſaith it is not: they ſay, <hi>Thy daughter is dead,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 5.35.</note> 
                  <hi>why trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest thou thy maiſter with prayers,</hi> and ſuites any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, now all hope is paſt? But Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Feare not, onely beleeue, and fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all,</hi> that perſwade thee to the contrary, euen Satan, fleſh, reaſon, nature, and all the World. For this commandement of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, is contrary to all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. All other comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the Morall Lawe, of naturall equitie, and Iuſtice, are ſeconded,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:1403:103"/> and ſealed by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of all creatures, to bee iuſt, faithfull, and true, and they perſwade to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of them: onely this commandement of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, is contrary to all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Heauen, and Earth are againſt it, and bid vs deſpaire, for there is no hope. This therefore is the greateſt obedience, and the cheifeſt worke, moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, and moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring him, as God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all creatures, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them all, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, God will honour, and ſaue ſuch a ſoule, againſt all creatures. <hi>He that beleeueth in me, though he were dead, yet ſhall he liue. Iohn</hi> 11.25. Of all ſinnes, and ſinfull paſſions, its the hardeſt to reſiſt infidelitie, feares,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:1403:103"/> doubts; and of all combats againſt ſinne, to fight the good fight of Faith. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nature giues ſome ſtrength, and aide, to reſiſt other ſinnes, and naturall reaſon, but onely God and his word, to reſiſt infidelity. Nature, and all creatures, forbid this beliefe, that a dead man ſhould liue, and riſe againe. When we feele ſinne, and dead workes, which ſurely bring death in reaſon, ſenſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, &amp; courſe of nature, when wee feele a dead heart, and ſee nothing, but dead bones, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.3. <hi>that theſe dead bones ſhould liue againe,</hi> all creatures for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid vs to beleeue it, yet, Chriſt commands vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that he is the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and the life, to
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:1403:104"/> quicken the dead, and to truſt in his voyce, that the dead ſhall heare it, and liue, whatſoeuer the death be in heart, or conſcience, and whatſoeuer ſoule-murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring deſpaires, and feares, deſtroy the life, peace, and comfort of our ſoules, and conſciences, yet, if we will hearken to Chriſts voyce, and obey his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to beleeue his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of life, comfort, peace, willing, deſiring, and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring to beleeue, hee will quicken in vs the life of Faith, <hi>and fill vs with ioy, and peace in beleeuing, and make vs to abound in hope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.13.</note> 
                  <hi>through the power of the holy Ghoſt, Fulfilling the good pleaſure of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and the worke of Faith, with power in vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:1403:104"/>
               <p>Faith, hath God for its obiect, in two reſpects.</p>
               <p>Firſt, of his Perſon, and Diuine authoritie, which it beleeues ſimply, and onely, becauſe God ſaith ſo, and commands him to beleeue his bare Word. This is that ſpeciall honour, which Faith giues to God, aboue all creatures, that, though all creatures ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand vs the contrary, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neuer ſuch reaſons, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and probabilities; yet, wee will beleeue God, vpon his bare Word, and commanding vs ſo to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, becauſe he is God, &amp; ought ſo to be obeyed, and beleeued, though wee can ſee no reaſon for it. For if he be <hi>Iehouah,</hi> hee will giue Beeing to his Word, and hath Wiſedome, Power,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:1403:105"/> and will, to doe whatſoeuer hee ſaith, elſe hee were not God. Therefore, becauſe the Goſpel, a myſterie, and hid wiſedome, aboue the capacitie of men, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, is preached by Gods ſoueraigne commandment, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.26. and wee are commanded, to heare, and beleeue it: therefore we wil ſo doe, onely, becauſe God commands. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.16, 17. <hi>Faith therefore comes by hearing, and hearing by the word, and commandement of God, which commands prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and hearing, as the meanes to beget Faith.</hi> Now all wicked men, and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers, doe not onely not beleeue, when the Word is offered, but by a rebellion of will, they refuſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> 
                  <hi>and caſt the word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:1403:105"/> their backes,</hi> and the commaundement to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and will not ſubmit themſelues to the meanes of beleeuing, in obedience to God, becauſe God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them. But if they heare, its when they liſt themſelues, &amp; whom they pleaſe, and in ſuch maner, and meaſure, as likes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as learned, eloquent preaching, and for ſuch ends as they thinke fit, and not in ſimple obedience to God, as his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ordinance, to get Faith, and by Faith, all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing good in Chriſt, but in obedience to their owne reaſon, and luſts. Such men, their infidelitie is not in them an infirmitie, but an obſtinate rebellion, as of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to God, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:1403:106"/> of his commandement, and of Faith.</p>
               <p>The Saints doubt, and feare, but againſt their wils, highly prizing faith, and earneſtly deſiring it, they ſubmit themſelues to the commandement of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, which they obey as well as they can, at leaſt in conſent, and earneſt deſire to obey, and beleeue, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting themſelues gladly to all counſell, and meanes of getting Faith, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.16. I conſent to the Law, that it is good. So they conſent, to this Lawe of Faith, as ſingularly good, <hi>and delight in it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.22.</note> 
                  <hi>concerning the inner man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this bee true Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Law Morall, thus farre to obey, though we cannot fulfill the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement:
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:1403:106"/> then alſo is this rather true obedience to the Law of Faith, to be willing, and deſiring, and to labour to beleeue vpon Gods commandement, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting our vnbeleefe, and ſtriuing againſt it, when we cannot beleeue as wee would: Eſpecially the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of beleeuing the myſterie of the Goſpel, ſo farre aboue the capacity of Men and Angels, being a commandement infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harder then all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Lawe Morall, which haue their ground in nature by creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But to beleeue that God will quicken the dead, and iuſtifie the vngodly, and ſaue ſinners, &amp;c. Is a commaundement againſt nature, reaſon, and ſenſe,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:1403:107"/> and all creatures, and all power and authority in heauen and earth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding to beleeue the contrary. Yet this honour doth Faith giue to God, commanding vs to beleeue, and this obedience, that we renounce Nature, and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Rule, and Authoritie, and all creatures, to obey God, as moſt wiſe, true and faithfull, and King &amp; Prince only, that by his Word creates and commands all things;<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Receiuing his Word not as the word of men, but as it is indeede the Word of God, of ſoueraigne</hi> authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with vs aboue all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Faith hath God for its obiect, beleeuing God, as firſt and chiefely for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, his Perſon and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:1403:107"/> ſake; ſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place for the reaſons and proofes giuen by him. Some things we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue ſimply and only vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods commandement, becauſe he bids vs beleeue them, though he giues vs no light of reaſon, nor no proofe to our ſenſe by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, as the principles of Religion. Some we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, becauſe he giues vs cleere reaſons, and prooues his words by ſenſible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and vndeniable arguments to reaſon and ſenſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.140. <hi>Thy Word is prooued most true, therefore thy ſeruant loueth it,</hi> as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.29. <hi>Thou haſt ſeene Thomas and beleeued, bleſſed are they that haue not ſeene and haue beleeued, only</hi> vpon my commandement,
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:1403:108"/> 
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.12. If <hi>when I tell you earthly things ye beleeue not,</hi> that is, doctrines demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated with naturall ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble proofes, to your reaſon and ſenſe here on earth; <hi>How will ye beleeue when I ſhall tell you of heauenly things,</hi> aboue reaſon and ſenſe to conceiue, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you to receiue them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bare diuine authoritie, without reaſon &amp; grounds to beleeue? If we beleeue not God, nor honour him as true in his word, proued by good reaſons &amp; grounds reuealed to vs, and light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to our vnderſtandings, much leſſe will we beleeue him vpon his bare word, to honour him as God.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the firſt part of liberty by Chriſt, is of heart our <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by which
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:1403:108"/> we goe boldly to God, and to the Throne of his grace</p>
               <p>The ſecond is that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our mouth, to ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke to God. Maruailous large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mouth, and liberty of ſpeech, to ſpeake to God freely, in prayers, praiſes, and thankeſgiuings.</p>
               <p>Wee are all by nature dumbe and deafe to God, by a dumbe and deafe ſpirit of Satan: poſſeſſing and dwelling in vs, till Chriſt redeeme vs to be his owne ſeruants, we neither can nor dare ſpeake to God. But Chriſt our Lord giues vs in Redemption, an open large mouth to ſpeake to God, to ſing to him, and praiſe him, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>Open thou my lips, that my mouth may ſet forth thy praiſe.</hi> Iſa. 51.11. <hi>The Redeemed of the
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:1403:109"/> Lord ſhall come and ſing in the height of Sion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 40.2. Ezek. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God is ſaid to put a new Song of praiſe in our mouths, and to poure on vs a large ſpirit of ſupplication, to take to vs words,</hi> as <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>For this is the principall End of our Redemption, that we ſhould haue liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſpeech to call on God and praiſe him, that our mouthes ſhould be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to him, to ſet forth his glory, as it was the chiefe end of our creation. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.21.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>This people haue I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for my ſelfe, they ſhall ſet forth my praiſe. Therefore with the mouth we confeſſe vnto ſaluation,</hi> and ſing to the Name of the Lord. Therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth, <hi>That God would not vtterly take the word of truth out of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note>
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:1403:109"/> 
                  <hi>his mouth.</hi> And this is Gods couenant, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.11. As its the End of our creation and redemption, and the chiefeſt part of our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; So the contrary, is the chiefeſt part of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery by our Fall, to haue our mouthes ſhut vp as beaſts, from prayers or praiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> The nouriſhing vertue of meate feeding the heart and ſtrengthning it, opens the mouth to ioyfull praiſe, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.26. &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.5. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.4. They ate and dranke, and praiſed the gods of ſiluer and gold. How much more then the Saints fed with Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood, and that plenteous redemption that is in Chriſt, praiſe him?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Out of the abundance of
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:1403:110"/> the heart the mouth</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged to poure out.<note place="margin">Math. 12.34.</note> If the Treaſure of the heart bee large, the mouth will large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpenſe. Chriſt is a moſt rich Treaſure in the heart of all ſtore of good, therefore the mouth muſt needs be anſwerable to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and confeſſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold the myſterie of Chriſt, and to praiſe him. Where there is nothing of God and Chriſt in the heart, there is no mouth opened, but ſhutte vp to confeſſion and praiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Hereby we may know, if our ſinnes be pardoned, and we redeemed in heart and ſoule, conſidering how our mouthes are opened, and tongues vnlooſed, to Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logize for our ſelues, as 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. and to plead our
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:1403:110"/> cleering and Iuſtification in Chriſt, to pray and call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Name of the Lord, to praiſe and confeſſe his mercy and truth. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1. conſider the high Prieſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, whom we all confeſſe, as 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, by ioynt confeſſion of all, its a great myſtery, &amp;c. Haue we left booke prayer (though I ſimply condemne it not, but allow it in yong Chriſtians, while they are as babes, and nothing differing from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants) but true Chriſtians co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue not in this bondage but grow vp to this libertie <hi>to pray in the H. Ghoſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iude 20.</note> as the Spirit giues them vtterance; haue we a naturall liberty &amp; facillity of mouth to ſpeake of holy things, &amp; not as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> taught, by rote? Can
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:1403:111"/> we ſpeake more abundantly and fluently in the cauſes of God, then of any thing elſe in the world, and ſing more ioyfully of Gods mercies, waies and workes?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This is alſo an euidence of our future Redemption, and liberty in due time out of any miſery, if God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore open our mouthes, and inlarge the liberty of ſpeech to prayer, praiſes, thankeſgiuings. The Spirit of Redemption and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is now in vs, and hath begun our freedome, and will perfect it. If God were purpoſed to ſhut vs vp in priſon of perpetuall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of perdition from him, his face, and preſence, hee would alſo ſhutte and ſeale vp our lippes, that we ſhould not haue libertie to
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:1403:111"/> ſpeake and pray to him, &amp; make any ſuite, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But if hee giues our ſoules liberty out of the Diuels priſon, from that dumbe and deafe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to come to him in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and to tender our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to him, its an euidence, that he intends our perfect deliuerance and good iſſue out of all our troubles. If hee vouchſafe vs the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to call on him, to ſpeake or petition to him, its certaine, its his purpoſe to free vs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. laſt <hi>verſ.</hi> When a King is purpoſed to deſtroy a Rebell or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, he commands him to be kept cloſe priſoner, and not come forth, to make or preſent any petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to come into his ſight, or ſpeake to him: but if he
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:1403:112"/> giue him leaue to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, though with his Keeper in reſtraint, only with libertie to vſe his friends and beſt meanes, it ſhewes there is hope of his inlargement, and of the Kings purpoſe to free him. So if wee haue libertie to goe to Chriſt by Faith, and take him by the hand, and vſe him our Mediatour, by him to petition to God, and make our ſuites, its aſſured ſecuritie to bee heard and deliuered.</p>
               <p>Hereby wee may alſo know if we haue beene fed with Chriſt, &amp; haue drunke his blood and ſpirit, or the ſpirit obtained by his blood in the Sacrament; we ſhall then ſing and praiſe Chriſt &amp; his benefits, our mouthes will be opened, as <hi>Pſalme</hi>
                  <pb n="215" facs="tcp:1403:112"/> 22.26. and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.18.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe if we be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed of the Lord Ieſus, and his ſeruants by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, he will giue vs a new mouth, and language to praiſe and honour him. The receiuing of a new language is a note and marke, and indeede a bond of ſubiection. Thus the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Romanes did plant their language, the Latine tongue in the countries which they conquered; And the Kings of Spaine, cauſe the Indians to ſpeake Spaniſh. Whom God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers by his Word, hee plants his Word in their hearts, &amp; in their mouthes. Where Chriſt or Satan raigne in the heart, their language and voice, or tongue is in their mouth.
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:1403:113"/> If Chriſt dwell in the heart by faith, hee will giue a great <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the mouth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. with 12. <hi>verſe.</hi> and <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6.</p>
               <p>The Beaſt of Rome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted by Satan the Dragon, or the Dragon reigning in the Heathen Emperours, and their ſucceſſors, gaue them a mouth to ſpeake as a Dragon.</p>
               <p>As Chriſt eſpecially reignes in his Miniſters, and ſets vp his Kingdome in others, by them prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpel of the Kingdome; ſo hee giues them a ſpeciall mouth, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> aboue others. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. So he promiſeth to <hi>Moſes</hi> in a ſpeciall manner to be with his mouth, to conquere <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and to redeeme his people, and to
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:1403:113"/> giue his Diſciples a mouth &amp; wiſedome, againſt which all their aduerſaries ſhall not be able to ſpeake or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; but it ſhall conquere them, and all their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, pollicy, ſophiſtry, and all the wiſedome of this world, and of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this world, which come to nought. Mens beaſtly, prophane, earthly, and fleſhly ſpeech, mouth and language ſheweth, that they are baſe ſlaues and vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals to the fleſh, belly, earth, and Satan. Contrary, holy and godly ſpeech, and the Word and Truth of God in mens mouthes, holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of diuine things, ſhew Chriſt to reigne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. <hi>When the word of Christ dwels in vs plenteouſly, Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>and wee abound in all
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:1403:114"/> ſpeach, and in all wiſdome,</hi> as 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>not in excellency of humane ſpeach, &amp; wiſedome,</hi> but as 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. As God raignes by his word, and its his kingdome, ſo where he ſets vp his Kingdome, in any mans heart, and ſoule it giues him the lip of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, and a mouth of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as to Chriſt, ſpeaking with that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and not as the Scribes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>verſe</hi> the laſt. God rules and gouernes all by his Word. Hee ſtilleth the raging of the Sea, by his Word. <hi>Reu.</hi> 19. The word of God, is King of Kings, and hath many Crownes vpon his head, conquering the Beaſt, and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and ſends them to Hell, and the reſt, that is, the Kings of the Earth are
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:1403:114"/> ſlaine by the ſword, that comes out of the mouth of him, that ſits on the white horſe, that is, ſanctified god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miniſters, which ſword, is the goſpel of the kingdome.</p>
               <p>For Chriſt raignes by his Word, in the mouthes of his true Miniſters: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, Antichriſt raignes by the Temporall ſword. His Kingdome ſtands not in his mouth, &amp; word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, as of the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 11.5. <hi>Out of whoſe mouth came fire, to deuoure their aduerſaries,</hi> that is, the holy Goſpel, in ſpirituall, and powerfull preaching: For thus it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth true Miniſters to fight, and to kill their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, <hi>verſe</hi> 5. But the Beaſt that comes out of the bottomeleſſe pit, makes
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:1403:115"/> warre againſt them with the Temporall ſword, and kils their bodies, <hi>verſe</hi> 7, 8. for their kingdome ſtands in Temporall Power, Honour, and Dignity. Chriſtes Kingdome is his Word Preached: Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes Kingdome, and power, ſtands in Kings, and Princes power, the tenne hornes of the Beaſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he is armed to gore, &amp; wound the body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Adam</hi> to the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Babel,</hi> the Church of God was one, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, and all the ſeruants of God confeſſed one faith, in one language, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed their obedience, and ſubiection to the kingdome of Chriſt in one language, the Hebrew, the Primitiue holy Tongue, till the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:1403:115"/> of Languages came in, at the building of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel. In the Primitiue times, all the Churches, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes of Chriſt, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their obedience, and ſubiection to Chriſt, the Lorde that had bought them, by one vniforme confeſſion of Faith, till ſpirituall Babylon erected, brought a confuſion of Languages, and differing confeſſions of Faith, and of the worſhippe, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Chriſt in diuers articles of Doctrine, and Diſcipline, of differing formes of Churches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Sardis, Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> and <hi>Laodicea,</hi> which will continue till Babylon it ſelfe be deſtroyed, and then the vniuerſall Church ſhall be vniforme in all Nations,
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:1403:116"/> and one confeſſion of faith, both of Iewes, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, profeſſing their ioynt ſubiection, and ſeruice to Chriſt their Lord, in one forme of confeſſion of faith, in one holy language, and forme of worſhip, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God with a ioynt <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluiah. Reuel.</hi> 19.1. the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſtate of the vniuerſall Church, and the common forme of Diuine worſhip, and praiſing, from the firſt calling, and riſing of it out of Egyptian bondage, and Antichriſtian darkeneſſe to this time, is a new ſong be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne of God, now raigning ouer them, being redeemed from the tyrannie of Antichriſt; A new ſong of praiſe, and worſhip, not before heard for many ages, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.3.
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:1403:116"/> The ſong of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Lambe, <hi>chap.</hi> 15.3. the ſong of a ſmall number; <hi>chap.</hi> 14.3. But now that Babylon is deſtroyed, and both Iewes, and Gentiles called, and Church inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the comming in of the fulneſſe of the Gentiles, the common forme of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine worſhip, &amp; praiſing of God is altered, and brought to the firſt, and Primitiue auntient forme from the Creation, which is <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluiah.</hi> See <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
